- In the last lesson,
you have learned about Linux commands.
Now there are so many
Linux commands available
that sometimes it's difficult
to find out how to use them.
In order to get more information
about these Linux commands,
there is man,
which is also a command.
And it's the best source
to get extensive usage information.
A manual of sections that
define command types.
And many man pages also have examples.
And you can search in
man pages using slash.
Now, man is not the only option.
There are other documentation solutions,
but you won't be using them as much.
Known for interest has full
documentation available in info.
And pinfo is an easy way to navigate,
much easier than info,
but you will only use
them in exceptional cases.
I would suggest you focus on learning man.
It's really important.
Let me show you.
All right, let me start by using man
on the who command, for instance.
That's a nice and simple
command to get started with
and to explore the structure of man.
So on the top line,
you can see the name of the command
with the section number behind it.
Now you might wonder,
"Hey, if Linux is case sensitive,
then why on the top line
do we have who in uppercase?"
Well, that's because
of respect for history.
The very first man pages that were created
long, long time ago in the early 1970s,
and which by the way are kept in a museum
of computer history in
Mountain View, California.
They had this header line
on every single printed page
where you had the command in uppercase.
And that's why, out of respect for history
that never went away.
I'll tell you about these
section numbers later.
But section 1,
that is where you find commands
that can be used by ordinary users.
Now we have short
description of the command,
the name of the command,
and short explanation what it is doing.
The synopsis, which is
telling you how to use it.
In this synopsis, we
find different elements
that are quite, quite common.
Here we have the element
between square brackets,
that means that it is optional.
So you don't have to.
Here we have the three dots.
The three dots is a repeater
from the previous elements.
So you may use an option.
And the three dots is indicating
that you can even use multiple options.
And then we can specify
a file or arguments,
and well, that's between square brackets,
so that means it's also optional.
Notice the use of the pipe sign here.
The pipe sign is used as an or indicator.
So you use either a file,
or you use one or more arguments,
but you can't use both.
Then, and that's what's so cool about man.
You can see a description
of all these different options.
And in case you are wondering,
"Hey, didn't we see them
with --help as well?"
Yes, you did,
but not as much information.
And that's what you use man for.
Man is giving so much information.
At the moment you are done,
Use Q to get out of here.
Now let me use man on a command
that has a little bit more,
more information,
like man on RPM.
RPM is a Red Hat Package Manager.
And there, you can see it starts
with the synopsis as well.
And this synopsis is a lot longer.
And you can use the Space bar
to scroll through the man page
and get to the next page.
And as you can see, there is a lot here.
Now, if man pages are big,
and sometimes they are,
then you can easily search
in the man page using a slash.
Let me use slash
and let me find on query for instance.
You can see in the lower
left corner while I'm typing.
And I'm typing query,
and it highlights the first time
from that current position on
where it has found the word
that I'm looking for.
If you are searching for something,
use N for next.
So you can do that as
many times as you want,
to see all the different query options
that are available.
I also like uppercase G in man,
because uppercase G brings you
all the way to the end of the man page,
where you have see also,
and sometimes even examples.
The see also is for related commands.
And the examples, well,
that is for your examples.
No matter how big a man page is,
as you can see, 730 lines in this case,
use Q to get out of there.
So in Linux, there are so
many commands available.
And because there are so
many commands available,
the documentation in man
is organized in different sections.
And for administration,
there are three sections that matter most.
Section number 1 is
for executable programs
or shell commands.
Section number 5 is for file
formats and conventions.
You will use it for configuration
files, for instance.
And section number 8 is for
system administration commands.
That's indicating that you
need a root superpowers
in order to use the command completely.
And all sections are described
in a man page for man,
man man.
And if you want an introduction
to what a specific section
number is all about,
use man followed by the section number,
followed by an intro.
Let me show you.
Okay. So we were just in man for who.
Oh! No manual entry for whoa.
Just who.
And here you can see who
with a 1 behind it,
in braces.
That's a section number.
And a section number is in
all man pages, to the top.
Man RPM, for instance,
you can see section number 8.
For a full description
of the section numbers,
use man man.
And you can see the
description right here.
For an RHCSA level,
you only care about section 1, 5, and 8.
But if you get deeper
to the Linux operating system,
you might get interested
in other sections as well.
Like system calls, and library calls,
and kernel routines, and other options.
Now, if you want more information
about what section it's doing,
you use man followed
by the section number.
And now you type the word intro.
This works for all of the sections.
So here you can see
that it's providing an
introduction to system calls.
Now also interesting to know is
if you type man passwd,
what's so special about passwd?
Well, passwd happens to be an item
that is documented in multiple sections.
So I'm typing man passwd,
and it will show me the
first that it has found.
And if I get out of there using Q,
then it's done.
If you wanna make sure
you don't miss anything,
type man -a.
Man -a is for all section numbers.
Here I'm in passwd section 1 again.
I'm pressing Q.
And it's telling us,
"Hey, I found another one, passwd 1ossl.
Do you want to view?"
No, I want to skip.
So Control + D.
And then, I found another one, passwd 5.
And if you think,
"Well, 5, that's about config files.
I like that."
You press Enter,
and you can see it.
And once you are done again,
you press Q.
And this seems to be the last one.
Last thing that I want
to tell you about this.
If there are different numbers
where your command can be documented,
then you can pass a
section number immediately.
So if you type man 5 passwd,
you immediately had hit section number 5.
If that is where you need to
be, can be quite convenient.