- Now, using man is convenient,
but what are you going to do
if you don't know what command
exactly you are looking for?
Well, in that case, you should know
that all man pages are
indexed in the mandb
and you can use man -k or alternatively
the apropos command to search
the mandb based on a keyword.
And that's convenient if you
don't know which command to use
but you do know the keyword.
In the output, you can
find a lot of results.
And if you get too many results,
you can use the grep command
in the pipe to filter the results.
I'll show you how that works.
But when working with
mandb, you should notice
that mandb is built automatically
through a scheduled task.
And sometimes you are looking
for something very obvious,
and you don't get any results.
Instead, it's telling
you nothing appropriate.
If that is going to happen,
then you need to manually
trigger a rebuild of the
mandb using sudo mandb.
Let's go check this out.
All right.
I'm using man -K user,
which is checking in the mandb
if there are any items about user.
Oh no, I am getting nothing appropriate.
Well, there's a very good
explanation for this.
This is a freshly installed system,
and on a newly installed system
your mandb command
hasn't been started yet.
And you know what?
I already told you that
you should use sudo mandb.
But I think it's nice if we go check out
how to get to that information.
So, I'm using man man,
the man page for man
and now I'm going to search for -k.
So, that would be slash, look
at the lower left corner,
- k, and then I press enter
and it's giving me the -k in the synopsis.
That's not what I want.
What I want is what I see right here.
Remember, you can use N for next to repeat
the last search operation.
So, this is telling me a
short description equivalent
to apropos in bold.
The bold typeface indicates
that this is probably also a command.
So, I'm going to use man
apropos to get more information
about this apropos thing.
And in case you wouldn't know,
well, here you can see the apropos,
the database search by apropos is updated
by the mandb program.
And depending on the
installation, this may be run
by a periodic cron job or
need to be run manually.
So, that is exactly what's going on.
You wanna know more?
Type man mandb, the interesting
information right here
is the eight.
The eight is giving that this
is an administrator command
and being an administrator command,
I probably have to use sudo.
Let's try it without sudo first.
I'm using mandb, what do we get?
I am getting, oh boy,
I get "can't create,"
"no such file."
I get lots of errors.
It's not so very obvious that these errors
are because I am not running
this with sudo privileges
but here we go using it
with sudo privileges.
And now we can see that it
is updating the index case
for all of these man pages.
Can take a little bit,
shouldn't be taking too long.
And once it is done,
after it has generated all of
this output, as you can see,
it has added almost 8,000
different man pages.
So, now I can try my man -k user again
and that is working and, oh boy,
that's a lot of information.
But if you look at all that information,
you can see that we have
results from different sections.
Like section two, which
is about system calls.
We do not care about system calls.
They don't matter if you are
into Linux administration.
If you wanna do administration,
you need to figure out what
is it that you want to do?
Well, if the answer is,
I want to create a user,
then you need to think a little bit.
Is that something that requires
administrative privileges or not?
If the answer is yes, then
you probably need to search
for the appropriate command
in section number eight.
So, I'm going to use man -k user again
and I'm using a pipe sign.
The pipe is taking the
output of the first command
and it's sending it to the second command.
And the second command that
I'm using here is grep.
No worries, we will talk
about grep separately
in much more detail later, but for now,
I want to show you grep eight
which is going to filter
out only those lines
that have an eight in the text.
And there we go.
Here we have a list only of commands
that have been documented
in section eight of man.
And that includes useradd.
Well, probably that might
be the command that you
were looking for and otherwise, well,
at least the results are a
little bit easier to check
after the filtering.
So, that is how you can use man -k.
Man -k really is a convenient skill.
You might like having it on the RHCSA exam
because you know, on the RHCSA exam,
you don't have any internet access.
So, you need to get all
the information straight
from your system.
And that is why man is
so incredibly important.