- Another thing that is
really essential to know about
while working with Linux is the editor.
So let's talk about editors a bit.
Why are editors so important?
Well, editors are important
because Linux configuration
happens normally by modifying text files.
Plain ASCII text is used for many files.
But there are some alternatives
as well, like YAML,
which is common in configuration
management, like Ansible.
Or JSON, which is used often
as a data storage format.
Or XML which can be used as an
alternative to JSON and YAML.
In order to use all of these
files, you need an editor.
And editors can modify text files
without adding any formatting code.
That is what is important about editors.
There are two common editors on Linux,
and these are nano and vim.
Let's talk a little bit about nano.
Nano is the easy-to-use editor.
After starting it, you can
start editing text immediately.
And commands are shown
as keyboard shortcuts
in the lower part of the screen.
Let's go check it out.
All right, let me type nano, my file.
When I'm using an
editor, I like to specify
the name of the file that I want to edit
or if the file does not exist,
the file I want to create.
So I'm using nano, my file
and this is bringing
me the nano interface.
What is so convenient about nano?
Well, I can start typing
my text immediately,
like, hello, this is my file.
And, we can see all the available options
in the lower part of the screen.
There are two types of options.
There are options that start with caret.
Caret is control sign.
So control X is what you
are going to use to exit.
There are also options that start with
what we call the meta key.
The meta key on most
keyboards is the alt key.
You won't use them very much.
The most often used option is control X.
So let me do a control X.
The rest of it is happening in
the lower part of the screen.
So, save modified buffer?
Yes.
So, as you can see, I
need to press Y for yes.
And then, a file name to write,
well, I already provided a file name
so, I'm just pressing enter
and the file has been saved.
Can we check that?
Yes, we can.
LS minus L on my file.
And did you see that?
This is what we call best completion,
I'm typing an M, then,
I press the tab key,
and as I have one file only
that has a name starting with an M.
Here, we can see the file exists
and that's the file that we just created.
And that's how easy it
is to work with nano.
But still, even if nano is so very easy,
most people are using another editor.
Let's talk about the other editor.