- All right, let's talk
about the other editor, vim.
Now what's so special about vim.
Well, vim is vi improved,
and vi was introduced in 1976
as a screen oriented editor
which was pretty new in that time.
So vim is the improved version of vi
and it has replaced the
original vi command.
Some additions to vim, you can
use arrow keys, for instance.
In the original vi you
couldn't use arrow keys because
these were not common in 1976.
Now, because command
line work in the 1970s
was line oriented, and
not screen oriented,
vi was developed with advanced features
to program text file modifications.
And especially because of
these advanced features
vim is still the most
commonly used editor.
True, nano is a lot easier,
but vim is so much more powerful
that if you end up being
a Linux professional,
you should learn about vim anyway.
If I may give you a suggestion,
for best practice use
nano to edit text files
in an easy way.
Use vim if you want to get
respect in the Linux community
and the full power that
you can get from an editor.
In the end, once you are
used to working with vim,
things will go faster.
And that is why for all of
the demos I'm doing throughout
this course, you will only see
one editor and that is vim.
Now, in order to work with vim
there's a few things that you should know.
To start with,
different modes are available in vim.
There's a command mode
which is a default mode after opening
and use command mode to
enter editing commands.
You get to the command mode
by pressing the escape key
if you're not currently
in the command mode.
And in case of doubt, you can
also press the escape key.
The insert mode is where
you can enter text.
You can press 'i', or some
of the alternative commands
that I will tell you
about in just a minute
to enter the insert mode.
And after inserting text,
don't forget to get back
to command mode, to
save your text and exit.
Let me show you how this works.
So I am going to create a new file.
Hello.txt.
I'm using .txt, that
looks like an extension.
Notice that extensions on
Linux have no function.
It's just for the
convenience of the users.
It makes it easier to identify
what kind of file this is.
At this point, I am in the command mode.
So this is the vim command
mode in which I can type all
of these commands.
But that only makes sense if
I've typed a little bit before.
So I am going to press 'i' for insert.
Look at the lower left corner,
this is what it looks like now.
Now I'm pressing 'i', and it reads insert
which is indicating that
I'm in the insert mode,
and I am typing my text
and then I'm ready.
Now, once you are ready,
you need to go back
to the command mode to use
the appropriate command
and the appropriate command
in this case would be escape first
and then :wq!
I'll tell you about that
command later, but colon is just
because command starts with
a colon, W is for write,
Q is for quit, and exclamation mark is for
don't ask any smart questions, just do it.
So that concludes our
first session in vim.
My file has now been written.
And if you want to, you can
quickly check the contents
of the file by using cat.
Cat is for dumping the contents
of a text file on screen.
And look at that, it reads 'Hello World',
so we probably did something right.