- Now, the most
inconvenient thing about VIM
is that you need to learn commands.
Let's go check out some of
the most common commands.
There is escape.
We talked about it, no
matter where you are
press escape and you are sure
that you're in command mode.
You can use I, or A if you
want, to enter the input mode.
Where I is for insert and A is for append,
which brings you after the
current cursor position.
O is also convenient, it opens
a new line in input mode.
and :wq, is for write and quit.
Do notice the command is :wq not :qw,
because you can't quit and then write.
Also useful is :q!, which will
quit without saving anything.
That's what you wanna do
if you really are not sure
and the only thing you know is that
you wanna get out of here
without messing anything up.
dd is common, it deletes a current line.
And yy, well, yank, which
is copy the current line.
And no matter if you've
just deleted or yanked it
you can use P to paste it,
to get it back at the current
position of the cursor.
V can be useful for visual mode, press V,
then you move your arrow keys
and you can make a selection.
And after making the selection,
you can delete it using D
or copy it using Y.
Also very convenient is U.
U for undo the last operation,
because if you are learning VIM,
you will notice that every now and then
something magical happens.
And you want to get out
of the magical environment
well, U, for undo.
Control+R is convenient as well,
that we will redo the last operation.
So, if you have undone something too much
use Control+R to get it back.
That's not all, there's a bit more.
Like gg, which will bring you
to the top of the document
or uppercase G, which will
go to the end of the document
or /text which will
search forward for text
or ?text, which will
search backwards for text.
Then there is caret, which
will bring you to the start
of the current line
or $, which will bring the
cursor to the end of the line.
There's also a W, which
will move to the next word.
And one of my favorites is :%s/old/new/g.
Which is a global substitute.
It'll change all occurrences
of the text, old with new.
Let's go check this out.
So, I'm using VIM, vimdemo.txt
And well, here we are on the top
and I am going to use,
O, for open a new line,
just because I wanted to show you
that my cursor is one line lower.
And what do I type?
I don't know.
This is what really
matters in demos like this.
This is a simple modification.
I'm just going to use my arrow keys to get
just behind the back slash
and I'm using backspace to remove it.
Now, let's go for
something more intelligent.
I'm using yy.
What is yy?
Well, that is yank or a copy.
And then I'm using P, to paste.
Do notice that you can do
that as many times as you want
but you don't need to
forget to press escape
to get to command mode.
Hey, what I also like, and
which is not on the slide,
is :se number, that is
showing line numbers.
That can be convenient,
if you want to talk about specific line.
Now I'm going to use dd,
dd is deleting a line.
And instead of deleting individual lines,
you can use V for visual mode,
look at the lower left corner
which is showing that right
now, I have visual mode,
in which I can move my arrow
keys and press D for instance,
to delete everything or U, to undo,
if you did not want to
delete it anyway, good.
Let me go to the top of
the document using G,
and I need to use the G twice, so gg.
And next I can show you my
favorite command, :%s/don't/do/g.
Do you see how nicely
VIM is highlighting it?
And now you can see that
everywhere where we had don't,
we now have do, and I
think I'm happy with this.
So I'm pressing escape,
:wq!, to write, quit
and get out of here.
Now, there is so much
more that can be done
in a VIM environment, but
I don't want to scare you.
I think this is enough for now.
That's one of the big risks
for people who are
getting started with VIM,
information overload.
If I may give you an advice,
practice the commands that
you have seen on the slides.
These are my favorites.
And apart from these comments,
the other ones that I know,
I don't use them that often.
There's one more thing
that I want to show you.
And that is VIM Tutor.
What is that?
Well, this is your online course in VIM.
Start reading and just do what
the comment is telling you.
Like J, for instance, to
bring your cursor down
and L to bring it to the right,
and there you are in lesson 1.2.
It's a good investment of
your time to use the VIM Tutor
a little bit, probably if you
use it for half an hour or so.
You have learned enough about
VIM to get yourself started.
But hey, in the end, use
whatever editor you like.
You're more comfortable with Nano?
That's okay as well.
Even if that means that you
are probably going to miss
all of the powerful features of VIM.