- Okay, so if you need to find a man page,
man -k is probably what you want to know.
man -k password, is that
bringing what we want?
Oh boy, that's a lot of information,
and in this lot of information
can we filter it down in a convenient way?
I think so, let's use Q to get out,
and let's use grep 1,
because changing a password, well,
that might be something that
relates to section number one.
And I don't see anything
that looks like what I'm looking for,
so maybe we need to look
in section number eight.
Does that make sense?
Well, maybe this command
that I'm looking for
is a command that works for the root user
as well as an ordinary user.
Now, what do we see here?
Well, you see something nasty
and that is that man -k in this
case is not so very useful,
because I don't know if
you see any useful command
but I don't see the command
that I'm looking for.
So let me cheat and show you man passwd.
What do we see?
We see that the man passwd's showing,
"update users authentication token".
Now, you know what, man -k is looking
in the line that I have
highlighted right here.
And do you see the word password? I don't.
And that's why we don't see
it in the results either.
But if I would use man -k authentication,
(computer keyboard clacking)
then this is what we get.
And in man -k authentication,
yeah, there we see passwd.
Anyway, passwd is what we want.
Then use the man page for useradd,
and create a user with the name anna.
So man useradd,
here we can see this, the
description, the synopsis,
and in the synopsis, we
see the different users.
So I need useradd LOGIN.
Now what this is LOGIN?
Well, if you don't know,
you can get it from the description.
It will create a user
with a specific name.
Do notice that useradd
is in section eight,
so that means that useradd anna
is not going to be working,
permission denied.
We need to repeat that last command.
Let me do that by
pressing the up arrow key,
Control + A to bring
my cursor to the front,
and then I'm using sudo useradd anna
and that's doing so much better.
At least, after entering
the appropriate password.
So I created the user and likewise,
I'm going to use sudo passwd anna.
Why is that?
Well, do you really
think that ordinary users
can change one another's password?
Of course not, that's why we
need sudo superpowers here.
So it's prompting for the new password,
going once, going twice,
and now all authentication
tokens updated successfully.
That's good news.
The last part of this exercise,
use VIM to create a file
with the name users.
I'm using I for input mode
and I'm entering "alex" and "alexander"
and "linda" and "belinda".
And that is all that we need for now.
So I'm pressing Escape,
and after pressing Escape, I'm using :wq!.
Well, let me tell you, I'm
going to use a shortcut.
"ZZ", which will do exactly the same.
Now my file is written, committed to disc,
and we can see that right
here when I'm using ls -l.
Vim users, there we go,
here is the users file.
And that's all for this
lab, let's continue.