- Hi, welcome to Lesson 9.
In this lesson, you'll
learn all you need to know
about managing local user accounts.
I'll start by explaining
what exactly the purpose is
of these user accounts.
And next you'll learn about
setting user properties
and how to create and
manage user accounts.
Once you know how to do that,
you'll learn how to
define default settings.
Then I'll show you what is going on
in /etc/passwd and in /etc/shadow.
And after that,
we'll talk about group
membership and groups
as well as password properties.
At the end of this lesson,
you'll find the lab and the lab solution,
which help you to practice
all of these important skills.