- All right, before we are starting
this important lesson about users,
it makes sense to think a little bit
about what exactly is the
user, why do we need them?
What is the purpose?
So the philosophy of the user on Linux.
A user on Linux is a security principle
and user accounts are
used to provide people
or processes access to system resources.
That's the most important
thing that you should remember.
It's for people, but also for processes.
Processes are using system accounts
and people are using
regular user accounts.
And for both of them,
you need a user account.
And regardless of whether it's
for processes or for people,
you process the same.
In the next couple of
videos, you'll learn how.