- When defining users,
there are different properties
that need to be set.
And I wanna talk about them.
You set these properties in
/etc/passwd, here they are.
Start with the name.
The name is the name of the user account.
It's a human understandable
name, so it's for people.
Then there is the password.
The password is the secret that
is used for authentication.
It may be disabled, but for
people uses normally, it is not.
For system users.
However, they should
never have a password.
They should be disabled.
Shouldn't be possible to
log in as a system user.
Next is a UID, which is a
unique identifier for user.
The GID is another ID
for the primary group.
When you create a user,
every user is a member
of exactly one group,
which is called the primary group.
Then there is a so-called GECOS field,
which contains additional
non-mandatory information
about the user.
We have home directories
for the environment
where users can create personal files.
And finally, there is a
Shell, which is a program
that will be started after
successful authentication.
For ordinary users,
the Shell is normally set to bin bash.
For system users,
it should be set to bin false,
or anything that disallows
the user to log in.
Let me show you the contents
of this /etc/passwd file.
Okay. So, if I use cat on /etc/passwd,
we can see the contents
of this passwd file.
Just picking out two random lines.
We have a line FTP.
This is a user that can be
created by the FTP server.
And we can see that this
FTP user has a directory,
a home directory via FTP.
Which happens to be the environment,
where this user can work with,
can create files and stuff like that.
Very important, as this is a system user
the Shell is set to slash
sbin slash no login.
So, no matter what this user is not going
to be able to log in ever.
Here, we have the first person user,
use a student that's
our administrative user.
We can see that people users
normally start their user IDs
at number 1000.
And the home directory
is set to sub directory
in slash home.
And the Shell is set to bin bash.
So, that is what we need
for ordinary people to be logging in.
On some of cases, you can
also see users that have,
that do have a Shell, but which
is a very specific program.
Like here, the halt user,
which is used for halting your system,
a slash sbin slash halt.
Which allows you to stop your system,
or the sync user,
as the sync binary,
which allows this user
to synchronize Shells
to whatever you want
them to synchronize with.
So, that's all about the user properties.
As we can find them in /etc/passwd,
there are more properties
in /etc/skeleton.
We'll talk about them later.
Let's first go and create some users.