- This video is about
creating and managing users,
which in fact is super easy.
There is just four
commands that are involved.
Useradd, which allows you to create.
Usermod, which allows you to modify.
Userdel, which allows you
to delete user accounts.
And once you have created
or modified or deleted,
you can set passwords.
Well, probably not on deleted users,
but for the other users you can.
PassWD is how to do it.
Let's check out these commands.
So, in order to work with these users,
and probably from this moment on,
I will be in our root shell sudo minus I.
That's also something
that I would advise to do
on your RHCSA exam,
just open a root shell,
because it's about system administration,
and you need to be root
in order to do system administration.
So, if you use commands like this,
might be smart to use a little command
Minus minus help and
pipe the output to less.
And here we can see all the
different options that exist
for creating this user account.
So let me use useradd to
create user Lori, for instance.
Minus U is an option
that you can use to set
the user id yourself, if you want.
So minus U, 2000.
Normally people users have
a user ID higher than 1000,
so anything goes.
And minus S if you want to set the shell.
So, if this user is supposed
to be never logging in
you set it to slash sbin
slash nologin, for instance.
I mean, all of these are
parameters that you can set
and to figure out if that works,
we'll grab Lori on ETC PassWD.
And there, we can see that the user
has been created successfully.
Is it useful? I'm not sure.
So, let's delete user
Lori again: userdel lori
Oh, wait, userdel, minus minus help.
Why is that?
Well, because I want to
check out some options,
in particular, these
options: minus RF Lori.
If you don't do this,
then some information
about the user might stick around,
and if you use userdel minus
RF, you remove the user,
you force the user off, and
everything is clean afterwards.
And that's all for now you need to know
about creating users.