- In this video, we'll talk
about user default settings.
The idea is you take care
of the default settings
before creating your user.
And that's especially what
you need to do on the exam.
You can use useradd -D to
specify default settings.
I advise not to do that.
Also, don't have a look
at /etc/default/useradd
because these are settings
that apply to useradd only.
That's pretty useless.
If you want to set user default settings,
you modify the config file,
/etc/login.defs.
Files in /etc/skel are created
to the user home directly upon creation.
So, if you want files to
be created automatically,
have a look at /etc/skel.
All right, now that you know
about these default settings,
let's have a look at /etc/login.defs
which is the most important
file for user default settings.
/etc/login/defs, here we go.
What do we have in this file?
We have a couple of important options.
It is a good read because many options
are well annotated and well explained.
But what you definitely need to look at
is what we find right here.
The Pass Max days, 99999.
You know how long that is?
That is 270 years,
count 270 years back.
That was before Napoleon in Europe.
That was before the Civil War in the US.
That was before Buzz
Lightyear landed on the moon.
Okay, so let's change this
and let's make it like, 99 for instance.
There's a couple of other options as well,
I do like "Home mode" by the way, 0700.
0700 means that only the user has access
to the home directory.
And we can set some other
properties in here as well.
Apart from that, there's
/etc/skel, you know what?
Let me use "touch/etc/skel/hello."
And now, let's do "useradd bill."
And also "passwd bill,"
so that Bill has a password as well.
Going once for the password,
going twice for the password.
And now, we can check
out what has happened.
Well, for users on a Red Hat system
they get a home directory by default.
And if I do an LS on that home directory,
look at that, it has copied
over the file from /etc/skel.
And if I would look up
"user bill" in /etc/passwd
we can see the ordinary
options, not a password one
because the password one
is stored in /etc/shadow
but /etc/shadow does contain
a couple of additional options
that I first separately need to explain.
So, let's talk about that later.