- All right.
An important task as
a system administrator
is that you need to be
able to limit user access.
That will make your system more secure.
How do we do that?
Well, there's a couple of options.
You can lock user accounts, temporarily.
Use usermod-L to lock a user
or usermod-U to unlock a user.
You can also set user accounts to expire.
Use usermod-E to do so.
And don't forget about the sbin/nologin.
sbin/nologin as a shell
is what you wanna do
for users that are not
intended to log in at all.
I already mentioned that this
is a setting that should apply
to all of these system users.
Now let me show you
how to lock an account.
Okay, so I am going to start
using usermod-L on Bill
which is doing a lot, though
it's not telling me anything.
In order to figure out
if it was successful,
passwd-S on Bill is convenient.
And what do we see?
We see password for user Bill is locked.
That's a result of the usermod-L.
Now usermod-U.
Well, there we go.
Password is set.
So the password is no longer locked.
Now let's get back to the locked password.
So now user Bill is locked again.
And, if we grab user Bill on ATC shadow,
which is a file where
encrypted passwords are stored
we can see the encrypted password.
It's the long string right here.
And if this encrypted password
starts with an exclamation mark,
exclamation mark means
that it's currently locked,.
Cannot be used.
So you could even do that yourself.
If you have a user, you
temporarily want to lock that user,
put an exclamation mark in
front of the password string.
Compare that to user Lisa who
has double exclamation mark,
that's what you get if a
password has never been set.
Now we have used usermod
to lock this user account.
And usermod is one way of doing it.
You can also use passwd
for similar functionality.