- An important property of
the user is group membership.
Each user must be a member
of at least one group.
That's a primary group,
and the primary group is
created automatically.
That happens when you create a user.
At that moment,
a primary group with the
same name of the user
is created as well.
Primary group membership is
managed through /etc/passwd.
The user of primary group is so important
because it becomes group-owner
if a user creates a file.
Additional groups can be defined as well.
That's a secondary group membership,
and the secondary group membership
is managed through /etc/groups.
Secondary group membership
is normal, convenient.
If a user needs additional
access to some functionality,
think of the group wheel, for instance,
that you would use to make sure
that the user can use des using sudo.
A user can temporarily set
primary group membership
using newgrp.
That might be convenient
if you want to take some functionality
after your account has been changed
without logging in again,
because if properties
of a user are changed,
the user needs to log in again
to make these properties effective.
That's not always convenient.
You are currently logged in as a user,
and the administrator grants you access
to the group wheel, for instance,
just type newgrp wheel.
The id command is convenient because
it will show you which
group a user is a member of.
In the next video,
I'll demonstrate how to manage
groups and group membership.