- In this video, I'll show you
how to create and manage groups.
So groupadd is the main
command to add groups,
and guess what you are going to do
to delete and modify groups?
Well, you guessed it right,
groupdel and groupmod.
Lid is a convenient command.
Lid -g on the name of a group
will list all users that are
members of a specific group,
and that's convenient
because group membership
can be administered in
two different files,
which is etc/group as well as etc/passwd.
Let's go check this out.
So here I have the
command id for user Anna,
and I am going to add a
new group, groupadd sales,
and I want to make sure that user Anna
is a member of the group sales.
Now, how do we do that?
Haha, not groupmod, because groupmod
has a limited number of options.
How are we going to do that?
Well, groupmod is one thing,
it has its option -U to specify users.
You can also use usermod - -help,
and usermod - -help, this is option G,
but be careful.
G is new list of supplementary groups.
That means that old supplementary
groups are overwritten.
So groupmod might be the better option.
Groupmod -U anna sales, for instance,
and that seems to be successful.
So let's use id on Anna again
and we can see the user Anna
is a member of the group sales.
If you want to see all users
that are a member of this group,
lid is what you can use.
So lid -g sales will print
a list of all the users
who are currently a member.
This is particularly interesting to do
on groups that are important,
like wheel, for instance.
Lid -g wheel.
Yeah, I'm happy to see that
only you as a student currently
is a member of the group wheel.
And I guess this is about
all you need to know
about creating and managing groups.
So let's continue.