- The last thing that you
need to know about users
is how to manage passwords.
So, let's talk about passwords.
Passwords are stored in an
encrypted way, in etc shadow.
There, you will find an encrypted string
and this encrypted string shows
three pieces of information
the hashing algorithm that was used,
the random salt,
and the encrypted hash
of the user password.
But Hey, do you really
need to know about it?
No, This is nice to know.
If you think that in etc shadow
the password is stored
in an encrypted way,
as long as you know that, then we're good.
Now, how do we manage password settings?
Basic password requirements
as we have already seen a set
in etc, login, or defs.
For advanced password properties,
you can use Pluggable
Authentication Models, or (PAM).
in Pam you have a model
the pam faillock model,
but that's nice to know.
We don't have to further
investigate how that is working
for our HCSA.
To change password
settings for current users,
use change or passwd, but
make sure that you are root.
Let's check it out.
So let's change user, change Bob
which is showing what?
This is very convenient,
it's going interactive
and that's exactly what
I would advise you to do
in case you have to do
stuff like this on the exam.
You don't have to think about anything
just follow the prompt.
Minimum password age,
Well, Bob should use the
password for three days
at least.
Maximum password age, seven.
I want it to be secure.
So every seven days, yes, that's right.
This user will change their password.
Last password change is
something that we don't
have to, to change.
It's normally set to the
day the user was created
if this is a brand new user.
Password expiration warning
one day is enough, seven days
if the maximum password age is seven
that doesn't make sense.
Password inactive is minus one.
So the password is not currently inactive.
And we do want an account expiration date.
So 2022-12-12
looks like a nice day to me.
And there we go.
User Bob has its password
settings changed.
So change minus minus
help is showing what?
Well, this is showing
that there is a minus L option
in order to verify you can use it.
So change minus L on Bob.
And there we go.
We nicely see all of the
parameters that we have just set.
And that's about all
that you need to know.
Passwd can do the same thing, but Hey
why would you wanna know
about two different commands?
If you can do all of the job
with just one command.
That's all, let's continue
with the end of lesson lab.