- All right, so let's start
with the password option
which is the login.defs.
We already talked about it,
so I just have to change the 99 to 90
to match the requirement here.
Next, we need to make
sure that the new files
are created to the home directory.
So touch/etc/skel/newfile,
anything in etc skel will be copied
to the user home directory.
It's mainly for configuration files
for the bash shell environment.
Then we need to create users,
anna, audrey, linda and lisa.
So useradd anna, do I have to do that?
No, we already have an anna.
Useradd audrey, that's the
user that I don't have yet.
How about linda?
Well, we can just try it.
We get an error if the user
already exists and that's okay.
We just need to make sure
that users are there.
Set password for anna
and audrey to password.
Let me do something funny.
Echo password pipe
passwd minus minus stdin
which is taking the password out of a pipe
for user anna and also for user audrey.
This is not a very secure option
because if you don't do anything,
it will be kept in memory.
But this is definitely something cool
for automated solutions.
Now we need to disable the passwords
for user linda and lisa.
Did you know that you can
also do that using passwd?
We have seen that with usermod
but I'm going to use passwd.
Lock the password for the named account.
That's what we need.
So passwd minus l linda will lock you,
so linda and lisa will be locked as well.
Then finally, we need to create
the group profs and students
and make user anna and
audrey members of profs
and linda and lisa members of student.
So groupadd profs
and groupadd students.
And then what was this nice option again?
Groupadd minus minus help.
Hey everybody, this is really something
that I would recommend to
do on the exam as well.
On the exam, you will have these moments
where you think, oh, what
was this option again?
You don't remember.
That's no problem.
Just use minus minus help, so
that we see groupadd minus u
anna and audrey
on profs.
Oops, did I really do
a groupadd? My mistake.
That should be a groupmod.
But hey, it's convenient to see
that groupadd can use the same options.
And now let me do an lid
on profs to figure out
which users are a member.
And next, let me use
an lid minus g on profs
to verify that this worked out all right.
And yeah, it did.
And now we can do it right from the start.
Groupmod minus U lisa
and linda on students
and lid minus g students
and what do we see?
We see the members of this group
and that is how you
could have done this lap.
Of course, different
solutions are possible,
but in the end the only thing
that matters is the result
and that's what we have right here.