- On Linux you will find many tools that
allow you to read a file
or to check contents from a text file.
Let's have a look at some of them.
To start with there is less.
So the big question is, is less more?
Well, more was the original file pager
and less was developed to offer
some more advanced features.
And as a reaction to that,
more was developed a bit more.
But still to do more, you should use less.
In particular, in less you
can easily scroll forwards
as well as backwards in files.
But for some reason,
that functionality has never
been implemented in more.
You can also work with first
and last lines in files.
Head is what you can use to show
the first couple of lines of text files.
By default, if you
don't use any arguments,
it'll show the first 10 lines.
And tail is showing the last 10 lines.
You can use a number
behind these command to
specify any other number of
lines that you want to see.
And before that number
you can put minus N,
but that's optional.
So a head minus N one will work,
but head minus one will also work.
Let me show you.
So I am using head on ETC pass WD,
which is showing the first 10 lines
of ETC pass WD, the user file is.
And if I use head minus
three on ETC pass WD,
well, we see the first three lines only.
And if I change that command
and replace head with tail,
you guess what's going
on, last three lines.
So you can even combine
them if you want to.
If I use tail minus
three, ETC pass WD, pipe,
head minus N one, just to show
you the syntax difference.
We have the first line out
of the last three lines of
ETC pass WD.
What I like about head and
tail is that they are simple.
There are typical Linux
utilities, simple but powerful.
And if you combine them,
you can do a lot with them.
Another useful command is cat.
Cat is also one of the simple commands.
It dumps stack file contents on screen,
and it works pretty well if
your file is not too big.
If you wanna see something
about a layout of a file,
you can use minus uppercase A to
print non printable characters as well.
Or minus B which numbers lines or
minus S to suppress repeated empty lines.
It cleans it up a little bit.
And tac, well, tac is probably one of
the most useless commands on Linux.
It's doing the same, but in reverse order.
Somebody at some point in time thought,
"Hey, let me have fun.
"And let's program cat
the other way around."
And that's what resulted in tac.
Is there anyone using it?
I don't know, but let's check out cat.
Cat is useful enough.
So let me use cat minus A on ETC hosts,
which is doing what?
Well, do you see these dollar signs?
These dollar signs are the
non printable characters.
So this minus A option in fact
can be very, very useful to
find if there are any
unexpected characters in a file.
Or cat minus AB,
which is showing line numbers as well.
And minus S, does that
make sense in this case?
Well, not really, because
there's no empty lines, but hey,
let's have a look at tac ETC host.
Do you see how cool it is?
Opposite order.
Once more, let's get back to the slides.
There is a few other tools
that we need to talk about
like cut and sort and
tr, and you know what?
I'm just going to demonstrate
the demos that you can see on the slide
so that we can analyze
and try to understand what is going on.
So let's start with cat minus D column.
Minus D in cut is a delimiter.
It's a field separator,
because if you are going
to address fields like,
like you do with a cat utility,
you need to tell cat how it
can recognize the fields.
So here we say, "Hey, cat,
"fields are recognized by a column and
"I only see field one."
And there we go.
The first field.
Now this is an unsorted list.
If you want to sort it, pipe it to sort.
The sort command itself has
options to filter out columns as well.
I like to use them in a pipe.
Keep it simple so that
you don't have to memorize
all of these options.
A little bit different is the tr command.
The tr translates.
Well, can you really call it translate?
Let's have a look.
If I use echo, hello, pipe tr, AZ, AZ.
Then we get hello in uppercase.
If you want to do it a
nice way, you better use
colon lower colon between square brackets,
and colon upper colon, also
between square brackets.
And that's doing the same.
Now, why is this better
for languages that have
special characters in file names?
AZ, AZ, this works for ASCII.
This works for anything.
Hey, there's one little thing
that I want to show you.
Let's do tr A L M Z, which is doing what?
Hey, it's transcribing the
contents of this hello string.
Also something that you
can do with a tr utility.
You'll notice that tr is
particularly useful in scripts.
If you wanna make sure that
the case you are getting is
either in uppercase or in lowercase.