- We have already seen
grep a couple of times.
And that is because grep is one
of the most awesome tools
that exists on Linux.
It's an amazing tool to find
text in files or in input
and you can use it in many different ways.
You know what, let me just
show you the examples.
And instead of talking about the slides,
let me run these examples for you.
So, let me start with
ps aux, ps aux by itself
is listing all the
processes currently running
and some interesting
options for these processes.
Now, what if you just want
to know about one process?
Well, then you can grep on it.
I use ps aux pipe grep ssh.
And in the result,
we can see the line that
contains the text "ssh."
Oh boy, there's one
thing that I need to do,
pipe grep
- v grep.
Which is doing what?
Grep -v is excluding from the result.
You know, if I would like
to use this in a script
or something, then I'm
interested in the first result,
not in the second result
because this is the grep command itself.
And by using grep -v grep,
I'm telling grep to filter out
all lines that contain the text "grep"
and then the result is pure
and you can use it in something else.
Another example of grep is on file.
So, if I use grep
student on star,
then what do we get?
We get a list of all files that
contain the text "student."
Now,
as we have seen before,
we have a little bit too
much of error messages.
So, let's filter the
error message a little bit
and send the error outputs
to the null device.
Now, in case you are not really sure
about the case of the string
that you are looking for,
grep -i is convenient,
-i for case insensitive.
What I also like a lot is
the after and before options.
The after and before
options are very convenient
if you analyze configuration files,
like grep
- A 5
- B 5,
we need spaces
to separate the option
from the option argument.
And what are we looking for?
Well, I'm looking for,
Allow in etc ssh
sshd underscore config,
which is showing a couple of parameters
like allow agent forwarding,
but also the five lines
before and the five lines after that,
because you might be interested
in seeing what exactly
is in front of it and behind it.
Last example for now,
grep -R
root or star,
which is doing a recursive grep,
not only in the current directory
but also in all of the subdirectories.
Hey, but one thing, do you see the result?
The result is really like
file name matching a line.
Wow. Can we also see just the file names?
Of course you can, grep -RL root star.
And there we go,
all the names of the
files in etc that contain
the text "root."