- Did I already tell you
what grep stands for?
It's a generic regular expression parser.
So, what is a regular expression?
Well, regular expressions
are text patterns
that are used by tools
like grep and others,
and they are very, very powerful.
Always put your regular expression,
or regex as it's also called,
between single quotes.
And don't confuse regular
expressions with globbing.
Globbing are shell wildcards
and regular expressions
are regular expressions.
And the confusing thing is
that the regular expressions
look like file globbing,
but they are not the same.
And that is why it's so important
to put your regular expression
between single quotes
to avoid interpretation problems,
especially if you are going
to use special characters,
as you can see in this example right here,
where we grep for a star in a star.
Now, regular expressions
can be a bit confusing.
They only work with specific tools,
like grep, and vim, and awk, and sed.
And sometimes these specific tools
have their own subset
of regular expressions.
That means that what
might work in one tool
doesn't have to work the
same way in another tool.
That makes it a bit confusing.
If you want, you can check the man page,
man 7 regex, for details,
but I can tell you,
that's a man page that
is heavily overloaded
with information you
don't wanna know about.
Maybe you're better off
just trying to understand
the examples that I'm going to show you.
Before I'm doing that,
let me explain why regular
expressions are confusing.
Well, the confusing part is
that there are several sets
of regular expressions.
The basic regular expressions
work with most tools.
Extended regular expressions
don't always work
and use grep -E if it's an
extended regular expression.
And some scripting languages, like Perl,
come with their own regular expressions.
And that's going to be problematic.
If you Google for a
regular expression example,
and it happens to be an
extended regular expression,
and you use it in a tool
that doesn't do extended
regular expressions,
well, it's not going to work,
and that's confusing.
So here, on the slide, we
have a couple of examples,
and I am just going to run these for you.
Okay, the best way to try to understand
these regular expressions is
by having a look at a file.
I created this file for you.
So let's start with a
simple regular expression,
grep single quote l on users.
What is this going to do?
Well, we just need to understand
what the regular expression is doing.
This is printing all lines
that match the pattern l.
And you can see there's a couple of them.
Now, if we put, as we call,
an anchor in front of it,
the caret, then we can
see lines starting with.
So caret string is for
lines starting with.
You can also do the opposite, like anna$,
which is for lines ending with.
And that is giving a
match on leanna and anna
but also on bananna
because, in the end,
the regular expression
isn't checking if it's a word or whatever.
Now, if it's about
words, you might like \b.
So, what is that doing?
Well, grep anna\b
on users is giving a match on anna.
Anna is a word.
So, how can we see that?
Well, we can see that because
annabelle is not there.
It's also starting with anna,
but there's no space
between anna and belle,
and that is why.
Now, kind of confusing
in regular expressions
are the repeating operators.
Let's do grep b.*t
on users, which is giving what?
Well, it's giving a lot of results,
but how do we explain the result?
Well, we have two things
in the regular expression.
We have a dot.
The dot is for one single character.
And then, we have the star.
And the star is for zero or more times.
So that means that we may or
we may not have one character,
and it can also be multiple characters.
And, in case you think
that is too confusing,
let me make it a little
bit more confusing even
by including bt so that we
can see what is happening.
Well, bt is also included
because the star is the
modifier for the dot,
and it stands for zero or more times.
Do we also have one or more times?
Yes, we do, and that will be the plus.
Hey, nothing?
Yes, that's right. Nothing.
And that is because this is an
extended regular expression.
So grep -E, and now we
can see that it works.
Likewise for the question mark,
also an extended regular expression.
And this question mark
is for zero or one time.
Now, in regular expressions,
it can also be useful
to search for characters
that occur a specific couple of times.
So let's do grep on bo
slash curly brace.
Confusing the slash,
but that's to take away
the special meaning of the curly brace.
3, which is the repeating operator,
which, again, has a curly brace behind,
and then we have a t,
and we do that on users.
And what are we getting?
We are getting nothing.
And is that something
that we can understand?
Yes, we can because there was no pattern
matching exactly three times an o.
Now, one last regular expression
that I want to show you
is the either/or, which is an
extended regular expression.
So I'm using grep -E.
Between single quotes
and curly braces again,
svm pipe vmx
on /proc/cpuinfo.
And, oh boy, we have neither of them.
What is this?
Well, proc/cpuinfo is a kernel file
in which you can see
properties of your CPU.
And, with this option, I'm checking to see
if either the svm or the
vmx property are available,
which would indicate that this system
is capable of virtualization.
Well, apparently, it's not
because we don't have a match here.