- In this video, I wanna talk about awk.
So what is awk?
Well, awk is a very powerful
text processing utility
that is specialized in data
extraction and reporting.
It was developed in the late 1970s
when computers normally didn't even have
a screen attached to it
and you needed to perform
your operations line based.
And that is where awk is coming from.
So very powerful in analyzing fails
and performing operations
on specific lines.
And these operations are
performed based on selectors.
Now, there are so many things
that you can do at awk,
but most of these things
have lost their usefulness.
I am going to show you
a couple of examples
which I consider useful.
Okay, our first example
is awk minus F, a colon.
That's the field separator in awk,
and I am using print,
dollar four on etc passwd,
which is giving what?
Well, it's giving user IDs.
I'll tell you about these later.
Now, let me show you how
awk can become useful
using awk minus F colon, and
next between single quotes,
I'm putting student and
them between curly braces,
print dollar four,
etc passedwd,
which is doing what?
It's printing dollar four
but only for lines at max, a text student.
And in fact, this is something that
is actually a pretty
complex scripting operation
in one single line in awk.
Also pretty common is the NF.
Now what is NF, if I use awk
print dollar NF, etc passwd.
Showing the last field.
This dollar NF is the
last field in the line.
And that's very convenient
if you don't know exactly
how many fields there are.