- In this video, I will tell
you a little bit about sed.
Sed is a stream editor, used
to search and transform text.
Also one of these tools that
was created in the 1970s
which was used a lot,
but nowadays isn't used that much anymore,
but still there are useful
things that you can do with sed.
It focuses on searching for text
and performing an
operation on matching text.
And here on the slide,
I have three demos that
I want to show you.
So, let me just show you.
So, first I'm going to show you
sed -n 5p on /etc/passwd,
which is doing what?
Which is printing a line
number five from /etc/passwd.
Then I am going to use
sed -i s/boot/beet/g on users
which is doing what?
Well, this is manipulating our users file
where we had a line that read, "boot"
and now it reads "beet."
Notice the g to the end,
I can show you what it's doing.
So, let me continue on these users
even if it's not users anymore.
And let me do bot bot bot bot.
One line bot four times.
So, I am going to use sed -i,
and we are going to replace bot with bet
but first without a /g.
What is the result?
Well, the result is that you can see
that it has to replaced
the first instance only.
And that is why we want to add g.
G for global.
Global means any occurrence within a line.
Now, another one is
sed -i -e 10d on users.
What is that doing?
Sed -i is for interactive.
Interactive means that the
change is written immediately
to the file.
Minus e is for edit
and the edit command that
we are passing is 10d.
Can you see the difference?
Well, the difference
is that it has just
deleted line number 10.
Before we had two bets,
now we have one bet only
and that's what you can do
with sed and so much more.
But my advice is don't let
sed and all confuse you.
There's so much that you can do with them
but there is also so much
that is not really needed anymore nowadays
you can do perfectly without.
Every now and then, the
examples that we've covered here
may come in handy.