- So to start with, we
need head, minus five,
ETC, pass WD, pipe, tail, minus one.
There we go. Fifth line
out of ETC pass WD.
Next, we need sed,
minus N,
five B on ETC pass WD.
Same result.
Then we use AWK and a pipe
to filter the last column
out of the results of the command PS AUX.
So PS,
AUX,
pipe,
AWK,
print,
dollar,
and F should be doing it.
And there we go. Last column.
Now, last column may give
you some unexpected results.
That's right, but that
requires further filtering.
That's not our mission here.
Now we need to use grep to
show the names of all fells
in ETC that have lines that
contain text root as a word.
So, let's do that in ETC
and let's use grep, root, slash B or star.
We do definitely need to remove
all these error messages.
So there we go.
And here we can see dex root.
Now, we have an interesting one.
Use grep to show all lines
from all files in ETC
that contain exactly three characters.
Is that an interesting one?
Well, in fact, it's a simple one.
We use carrot as a start,
dot dot dot for three characters,
dollar at the end.
And there we go.
All the lines in all the fells.
There's not that many of them.
Now we need to use grep to find all fells
that contain the string Alex,
but make sure that Alexander
is not included in the result.
All right, last one is to grep
on all fells that contain the string Alex,
but not Alexander.
Well, that will be a word grep.
And I'm going to show
you how it works for Anna
in our users fell.
There we go.
Here we find the works.
Now, confusing?
Yes, of course. But
slash B, slash B, slash B
for the beginning, slash B at the end,
that is showing it should
start a word, to end as a word,
and this is the result
that it's giving us.
So, that's all, I hope you
succeeded a little bit.
Nice, isn't it? Regular expressions.
They are very powerful,
but don't overestimate
the use of them.
On the scale of everything
you need to know
for the RHCSA exam, regular
expressions are not that big.