- In this video I will
show you how to work with
the bash shell.
But first we need to explore
what exactly the shell is.
Well, the shell is the environment
where the user interfaces
with the operating system.
Briefly, that's where
you type your commands.
Bash is the default command line shell,
and that is the place
where you will be spending
most of your time.
There's also a graphical
shell, which is known as GNOME,
or some people say GNOME.
From a graphical shell,
a terminal window running
bash can be started,
so you will end up with bash anyway.
And that's because the
bash shell is so powerful
and providing access to
all the functionality
that you will ever need
in your Linux environment.
So the bash shell provides many features
to make working with the shell easier.
And these include command line completion,
history, variables,
scripts, and much more.
We'll talk about these later.
So how do we use a shell?
Well before a user gets
access to the shell,
as we have already seen
the user must authenticate.
On a non-graphical system the
user will see a text prompt
asking for the user name and password.
And in a graphical shell,
the user can select the
account and password easily
from the graphical environment.
Let me show you.
So this is what the graphical
shell login looks like.
You see your account,
you type your password,
and then you are in.
Notice that the login procedure,
and the procedure to get
through your screen saver
are the same, the idea
is exactly the same.
So here you have the graphical environment
in which the shell terminal is open.
If you use Ctrl-Shift+
you can increase font size a little bit,
maybe you like that.
Let me also show you what a
non-graphical login looks like.
So in many cases you will be working
from a graphical environment,
but some systems come up with
a non-graphical environment,
and then this is what
your shell looks like.
And even if the environments
do look different
what counts is a command line.
Because no matter if it runs in a terminal
or in a completely text based shell
both of these are running the bash shell.