- All right.
So here we are in the GNOME
graphical environment.
In this class, I definitely
don't want to teach you
about the GNOME graphical environment
because most Linux services
you will be working
with aren't using any GNOME at all.
So let me start with the
most important thing.
There we go, Terminal.
If you double click
on the errors bar and then
use control shift, plus
you can increase the font
size to make it more readable.
And that is what your
terminal is all about.
If there's more that you wanna do
you can go to the terminal settings.
And these settings are
in the upper right
corner, under preferences.
And there's just one
thing that I wanna do.
I want to go to the profile.
My current profile is unnamed
and I want to disable the terminal bell
because otherwise you'll hear a sound
anytime you make an error
and that's just annoying.
Another thing that you might
like to do is in colors.
If you unselect use
colors from system theme
then you get this black
on a white background.
I like it because it's a
little bit more readable
so I'm going to keep that.
Now, I want to show you two more things
and in order to get there
I'm clicking in the upper
left corner on activities.
You can see my terminal is
becoming a little bit smaller
and we have this type two search.
This is a search bar
and like any modern operating system
you can just type what
you want to look for.
Well, I want to look
for my power settings and
know that it's not power off,
it's the second one, power
in the settings right here.
I'm clicking that just to make sure
that I have this screen blank
which happens after five minutes.
I don't want it to
blank after five minutes
I want it to blank never.
And that is about all that we need.
So if you know how to use a search option,
if you know where to find your terminal
then you will be good.
For the rest of it in this
class and also for RHCSA,
we are really not going to do a lot
in a GNOME graphical environment.