- In this video, I will tell
you about a special feature
in Linux, the virtual terminal.
So what is a terminal?
Well, a terminal is the
most important environment
that you are going to use.
It's the environment that runs a shell.
In a graphical environment,
multiple terminals
can be used on the same screen.
And that is why, even
if it's not very useful,
most Linux administrates like
graphical environments anyway.
In a text based environment,
only one terminal is
started from the console.
And that means that you can
see one thing at a time.
That's inconvenient
and that is why we have
virtual terminals.
Virtual terminals can be used to start
additional terminal sessions
and they are accessible
by using Ctrl[-Alt]-Fn
key keyboard sequences.
Like Ctrl[-Alt]-F2,
which is where your
graphical interface is hiding
or Ctrl[-Alt]-F3 up to F6
where you have some text
based terminals hiding.
Now, how do we work with
these virtual terminals>
Well you use the who or the w command
to see which users currently
are active on which terminals?
And you can use chvt for
change virtual terminal
to change between virtual terminals
or obviously you use the key sequences.
But in particular,
if you are in a virtualized environment
these key sequences are
not always accessible.
Let's go check this out.
All right, let me start by typing who,
where I can see that I'm user
student connected to tty2.
Tty is the name of the terminal.
Devices in Linux always
have a device name and tty2
happens to be the device name
for your standard terminal.
Now, if I would use chvt 3,
now what is going to happen?
Oh, something nasty has happened.
Couldn't get a file descriptor
referring to the console.
And you know why that is?
That is because I'm running this command
without root privileges.
We'll cover it later in more detail,
but already I want to tell you about sudo,
but before I type sudo,
I need to type sudo in
front of the command.
And now my cursor is to
the end of the command.
I like using the control 'A' key sequence
which brings my cursor to
the front of the command
which allows for easy editing.
And now I'm using sudo
chvt for super use sudo.
So with root privileges, run this command.
So here is my other terminal.
I use my username and password to log in,
and now I type who to
see who is logged in.
And there I can see that
I'm logged in on tty2
as well tty3.
And you know what, if
I do a sudo chvt again
to change to terminal four,
then it's asking for my password again.
And I have new login prompt.
And this new login prompt
is where I'm going to log in
as root and as root I'm going to type
the shortest command available, w.
'W' is giving kind of the same information
as the who command but
it's not only telling you
who is logged in and
where they are logged in.
It's also giving some more
environmental information
about these users.
Next I'm going to use chvt 2
and chvt 2 is bringing me
back to the graphical screen.
That's where it all started.
And this is all you need to know
about these virtual terminals.