- In this video
I want to introduce how to
work with Linux commands.
So Linux commands, there are many of them
and they all have common properties
and this video is just
about the common properties.
So most commands can
be used with arguments
and these arguments
further specify the use
of the command.
Options can be used to modify
the behavior of the commands
and to get a short usage overview,
use --help with the command.
And before I'm going to
show you how to use this,
one more thing.
Linux is case sensitive.
Almost all of the commands
are written in lowercase.
Make sure you respect the case,
because otherwise it won't work.
So, I'm on the command line right now.
And let's talk about ls,
ls is a command that lists files.
And if you want to know how it works,
use ls --help.
I like this --help a lot,
because it's showing a lot of information
about what you can do, sometimes so much
that it doesn't even fit on the screen.
If that happens, use a pipe sign
and send it to the less command.
We'll talk about these
in more detail later,
but that allows you to
see, screen by screen
what is happening.
And what do we see?
We see that ls has many,
many options, like -a,
which is equivalent to --o.
- a is what you call the short option,
the --o, you guessed
it, it's a long option.
They have exactly the same function.
So sometimes you can use
either the short or the long option.
Sometimes there is only a short option,
like right here for -f, or
there's only a long option,
like right here for the block size.
The nice thing is that this help system
will always tell you about it.
So what is the result?
Well, if I use ls -a, I see all files.
And all files,
that includes files that have
name starting with a dot.
We call those hidden files,
and, hey, what's the
difference with ls --o?
Well, it's just more typing,
but for the rest of it,
there is no difference.
We'll explore these
Linux commands a lot more
and you will learn a lot more
about them in the upcoming lessons.