- So here is what I needed
you to do for the lab.
You needed to log in.
Uh oh, we're already logged in.
Let's fix that in the upper right corner
you can see the play button,
and there is a log out option.
So, I am going to use log out
and that is going to log me out.
Now you can see that the
login screen is loading again
and I can click on my user
account and enter my password.
And then I'm back in the
graphical environment
in which I'm going to use
the search bar this time
to activate the terminal.
I do need to change the
settings of the terminal
and that's unfortunately
something that's not remembered.
So you need to resize the fonts and so on.
And I'm going to use who.
Hey that's interesting,
you have seen me logging out,
and while I logged out from tty2,
the sessions on tty3 and
tty4 have not been affected.
That's normal, but it's
something to be aware of,
because it means that
you might easily forget
about these sessions that are still open.
And if you do, that might be risky
from a security point of view.
So how about who minus minus help?
Who minus minus help is telling me
about all of these fantastic
options that can be used.
They don't matter at this point for now.
This is all I needed you to do.