- The Linux Filesystem
Hierarchy is very organized.
So let's talk about this standardization
before diving into the details.
The Linux Filesystem
is highly standardized
standard directly so defined
in the Filesystem
Hierarchy standard or FHS.
And its FHS was defined
by Linux Foundation.
Linux Foundation is the organization
behind all the Linux distributions.
And their main mission is
to keep standardization
between the different distributions
to make sure that even
if all the distributions
are slightly different, Linux
looks and fuels the same.
The link to the Filesystem
Hierarchy standard
is on the slight that
you can see right now.
I would say, check it out
if you are looking for any details.
The starting point of the
Filesystem is the route directory.
And in this route
directory different devices
might be integrated by using mounts.
I'll tell you about these mounts later,
but before continuing, I'd
like to show you a little bit
of what is going on in
Filesystem hierarchy standard.
So I'm using CD slash to
go to the root directory
because this root directory
is represented as a slash.
Then when we type LS
we can see all the directories existing
in this root directory.
Let's not try to cover all
of them at this moment.
We'll talk about them when it is needed.
Just a couple of them
the etc directory changing
directory, and I'm typing LS.
This is for configuration files
or the USR directory.
That's like your program
fails on windows here.
You can find all your
binaries, nicely organized
and user bin and user sbin where sbin
is super user binary
requiring a root privileges
and bin are the binaries
that would be documented
in section one of the
main page, if you want.
What else do we have?
Well another one that is pretty important
is the VAR directory.
The VAR directory is
used for temporary stuff
for a long time VAR log has
been a very important directory
containing log files,
but nowadays, as you will learn later
journal D is taking over
in journal D keeps its log somewhere else.
Also there's the TMP directory
TMPs for temporary files,
and this is the only
directory apart from the user
home directory, where any user can write.
If you want to check it, you
touch to create an empty file
with the name hello in this case
and look at that, start hello
is leading to me writing
a file with the name, hello.
Last but not least there's
the user home directory,
this type CD without anything behind it.
And you'll get automatically
into your user home directory
which can be verified if you type pwd,
if you wanna know more
about directories and which
is used for what type,
man hier, hier for hierarchy
this is the man page that is based
on the filesystem hierarchy standard,
and you will find it on Reddit
and it contains good documentation
of all of these directories,
including sub directory levels
and what exactly they are used for.
Now, this is one example
of why C also in man pages can be useful.
Do you see that?
That's man page file
hierarchy in section seven,
section seven is for diverse
kinds of documentation.
So if I use man on file hierarchy
then what are we going to get?
Now look at that.
We get a nice overview
of the way our Filesystem
hierarchy standard is organized.
It's a little bit of automatic approach
and you might like this approach
with more a documentation
about what is going on.