- While working with files,
there's a couple of commands
that you should know about.
To start with ls, which will list files.
Mkdir, which allows you
to create a directory.
Or cp for copying files,
and mv for moving files.
And there's rmdir for
removing an empty directory
and finally rm for removing files.
Let me demonstrate.
So right here, I'm in my home directory
and I am going to use mkdir filedemo
to create a new directory.
Ls, I like using ls-l for a long listing
so that you can see properties
of the files as well.
But if you make that ls-lrt,
you get a long listing that
is sorted by creation time.
Very often, if you look at it directly,
you are most interested in the
files that were added last.
And that is exactly what ls-lrt is doing.
The last added item is through the bottom
of everything you see.
Now, what can we do?
Well, we can copy files
like cp output to filedemo.
And do you see, tab completion
is really convenient
to complete the command
line, just press the tab key,
and the base shell will try
to automatically complete everything.
So I'm using cp output to filedemo.
And now if I use ls on filedemo,
I see the contents of this filedemo.
This is, by the way, something
that you don't always expect.
And if you want to see properties
of direct use, use ls-d
or ls-dl to see the long listing.
Right, I'm going to cd to
change directory into filedemo.
And I want to
copy slash atc slash ab*.
Anything starting with an a or a b to dot.
Dot is the current directory.
Notice that I'm getting a
couple of error messages.
Some error messages related to the fact
that I'm trying to copy directory
but I did not use cp with the
minus r option for recursive.
Let's expect it.
Another error relates to permission denied
on BRL API dot key.
Ah, that's an API key.
API key should be well protected.
So that makes sense that
we get a permission denied.
You can see the result here.
The result is a couple of files.
And I can mv, mv for move.
At/deny for instance, to
hello.deny or whatever.
mv is move, but mv is also rename.
And as you can see, the result is that
the original file no longer exists
and the new file has been created.
Now, did you like this demo?
I'm not sure about it.
It's just about managing files
and it's kind of boring,
so let's clean it up.
Rmdir, filedemo.
I want to remove my directory.
Too bad, rmdir is a command
that you can only use
to remove empty directories.
That makes it kind of not so very useful.
So better use rm-rf
- r is for recursive, -f is for force.
But Hey, I hope at this moment
you have found it out yourself already
by using rm--help
or man-rm, which is
perfectly documenting it.
Now, everything is gone.
Let's move further to the next topic.