- The Linux operating
system is all about files.
Files are so very important.
And for that reason, it's important
that you know how to find your files.
A couple of tools are involved.
Ls to start it.
Ls is used to list
files, not to find files.
Which, looks for binaries
in the path valuable.
Which, is a convenient command
if you are looking for an executable file.
Locate is not the most useful
file, but some people like it.
I don't like it very much
because locate uses a database
which is built by updatedb,
and if you don't updatedb,
the database locate won't find it.
If you wanna make sure
that you find your files
then there's just one
command that you should use,
and that is find.
Really. it's the most
flexible tool that allows you
to find files based on many criteria.
Let me demonstrate.
As this demo is becoming
a little bit more complex
and the commands are becoming longer,
I've also listed the
commands on the slides,
just to make it easy for you
to try this for yourself.
Okay, to start it, find /,
the first argument to find is telling find
where it should start.
Slash is always a good place to start
that's your root directory,
but do realize if you
start at a root directory
it can take a long time
before you see a result.
So I'm using find / -name hosts,
where I'm putting the
hosts between double quotes
and, oh no, I am getting
so many permission denied.
That is because this is really a demo
where we will be better
off in a root shell.
I'm opening a shell using sudo -i
and I'm going to repeat this demo.
Find / -name, between
double quotes, hosts.
It's always a good idea
to put your find argument
between double quotes.
Now, what do we see here?
Still a couple of error messages,
but we can blow away these error messages
by using standard error redirection
as we have learned before.
And now we can see that there
are two resulting files,
/etc/hosts, and etc/avahi/hosts.
The find command only
looks for exact match.
If you want to see files containing a text
then you need wildcards,
like in the Ls command.
As you can see here with the star before
and after the word hosts,
now it is giving matches also
on files like
ssh_knownhostproxy, for instance.
It really depends on
what you want it to do.
Next, let me use find / -type f,
- type f is useful if you
want to tell the find command
that the only thing that
you are interested in
is files, ordinary
files, not special files,
not directories, just ordinary files.
So am I doing here?
I'm looking for files with the size bigger
than a hundred megabytes.
And now we can see
between the error messages
that have been generated,
that there is a couple
of these files available.
For our next command,
we are going to search
in the etc directory.
So find /etc, is this time the
place where we want to start.
Then I'm using, exec grep -l student {} \;
Wow, what is that?
Well, we have the find command first.
The find command is
instructed to look for files
in the etc directory.
The advantage of using
the find command here is
that you can use additional criteria
like -size +1K or something like that.
And now we have -exec, -exec
allows you to run a command
on the result of the find command.
So the command that I want
to run is grep -l student,
and the grep -l student, well,
is followed by two curly braces.
The curly braces really
refer to the result
of the previous part of the find command
and make sure that you
are only going to look
for the text, student,
in files that are bigger
than one kilobyte.
Also notice the backslash semicolon,
backslash semicolon closes
a minus XX statement.
You can use multiple minus
XX statements, if you do,
then every minus XX statement
needs its own backslash semicolon.
And oh boy, I'm doing a wrong thing here,
minus uppercase K.
Well, I'm making a wild guess here
and I'm doing it on minus lowercase K.
And what do we see?
We see too many things that
are really not readable.
So this again is one of these examples
where we want to do error early direction.
2> /dev/null,
and here we can see a couple of files
that match what we were looking for.
We can even make this
command bigger if you want.
And if we do, I'm going to edit it.
But while editing, I'm
keeping the 2> /dev/null
to the end, because I don't want
to see any error messages at any point.
The 2> /dev/null results to the output
of the fine command.
So that is why it needs to
be at the end of the command.
And I'm going to add
a new -exec, -exec cp.
So after finding these files
and grabbing on the files,
I'm going to copy the files
that were found to find/contents/.
That's a typo, let me correct this typo.
So find/contents/, and then, oh, wait,
we need to close the find statement
with a backslash semicolon.
Hey, have you already wondered
what is backslash semicolon is about?
Well, semicolon as such can be used
on the bash command line
as command separator.
Just try, type Ls; who, and press enter,
and you'll see the result.
It'll first give you the output of Ls,
then it'll give you the output of who.
Why does that matter?
Well, in this case, the
backslash is making sure
that the semicolon is not interpreted
by the bash shell so that
find can interpret it,
because a semicolon has a
special meaning for bash,
and that is why you need the
backslash in front of it.
Now, let me use CTRL+A because
we need one more thing,
and that is mkdir -p, -p is for pass,
find/contents;
Here we see semicolon
and backslash semicolon two
times in the same command.
And what is the result?
Well, the result is that
find is doing its thing,
and if all went right, then
in find, directory, contents,
it has copied the files that it has found.
And that's enough for this
relatively complex example
of the find command.
Let's have a look at one
more example where I'm using
find /etc
- name '*'.
We are looking in all files.
Just to indicate, that
you can also specify
a pattern here if you want to.
And if you don't, well you
can do without a -name '*'
because -name'*' is a default behavior
if you don't specify anything else.
The command that matters here is xargs.
Xargs is taking the
output of the find command
and passes it to be used
by the grep command.
So the grep command is
going to grep its thing
on 127.0.0.1.
And the result will be that this command
will show you all files
containing the string 127.0.0.1,
which happens to be the
local looopback IP address.
You'll learn about that
later in this course.