- In this video,
I will tell you about
mounting file systems.
So mounting file systems is essential
for the file system hierarchy.
What is it about?
Well, if you are using a device,
it must be connected to a directory.
So, if you have a USB
thumb drive, for instance,
you need to plug it in.
And before you can use it on Linux
you need to mount it on a directory.
And that is what this is about.
We call it mounting the device.
Now the Linux file system
typically uses multiple mounts,
and different types of data
typically are on different
devices for multiple reasons,
like security, like manageability
and like specific mount options.
You may remember that
earlier in this course
we have installed a server
with custom partitioning.
And custom partitioning means that
you create a partition that you
mount on a specific location
to provide some additional
protection for your data.
Now, in order to mount a device manually
you can use a mount command that looks
like mount/dev/devicename,
and you mount it on a directory
like mount/dev/sdb1/mnt.
You insert a USB thumb drive,
typically you will see a device popping up
with the name sdb1, and
you want to access it,
put it on a directory
and mnt, /mnt is the most common directory
that is often used for mounting devices.
Convenient in this context
is to findmnt command.
Findmnt finds all that is
mounted at this moment.
And will give you a nice insight
of which device is on which directory
and it'll show you how your
current file system hierarchy
which shows as one,
is really spread over multiple
devices on your system.
Let's have a quick look
and do notice that
these topics are covered
in much more depth later in this course.
Let me show you findmnt
What do we find in findmnt?
We see in the left column directories,
and then we see what is mounted
on that specific directory.
In the output, there's
a lot of system mounts,
but there's also the /boot directory,
which is using /dev/sda1.
That means that if you go
to the /boot directory
and I type ls there,
then really we are on a
different device /dev/sda1.
If there are devices
that are not mounted yet,
another way to have look at them is lsblk,
for list block devices.
And this will show all the
devices available on this system.
There aren't very many,
because this is a very basic system
without much additional configuration,
but by the time you
start creating partitions
and logical volumes,
this lsblk command is going to
be a very important command.
And you know what?
You can even try to do a
manual mount, mount /dev/sda1.
/sda1 is already mounted on /boot.
I am going to mount it again on /mnt.
And as you can see, that is something
that is just allowed by
the Linux operating system.
But before this is giving me anything
that I am not expecting,
let me umount it again
to disconnect the mount,
which is required,
if ever you need to remove
the device, for instance.