- In this video, I will
tell you about links.
A link is a pointer to a
file in a different location.
You can compare it a bit to shortcuts
on other operating systems.
Links can be very useful
to make the same file available
on multiple locations.
And Linux uses hard links,
as well as symbolic links.
Sometimes the symbolic links
are also called soft links.
But that's incorrect.
You should call them symbolic links.
You can create hard
links with the ln command
and symbolic links with the ln -s command.
Before I'm going to show
you how to create them,
I'd first like to show you
how exactly these links are organized.
So let me make a drawing for you.
All right, let me explain
how links are organized.
It all starts with the inode.
The inode is the
administration of your files.
And from the inode,
you would go to the blocks.
That is the actual location on disk
where your files are stored.
Now, in order to access these inodes,
you assign a name to these inodes.
And the fact is that a link
or a hard link is a
name, not more than that.
The thing is that you
can have one hard link.
You can also have multiple hard links.
And if you have multiple hard links,
well, there are just multiple names
that are all at the same level.
There's no difference
between the first name,
the second name that you create.
It's just the same.
Now, there's also symbolic links
and the difference is
that the hard link points
to the inode directly.
The symbolic link points to a hard link.
And that explains very well
what a dependency is.
So you can have multiple
symbolic link to a hard link
but if you have multiple symbolic links
but if you have a symbolic link
and the original name is removed,
then the symbolic link becomes invalid.
Now, symbolic links do
add some flexibility
but this is really something to realize.
Before I'm going to show you
how to create these links,
I'm gonna show you how I'm
using them myself on my MacBook.
MacBook, that's not
Linux. Yes, that's right.
But macOS is a kind of Unix
and Unix is very familiar to Linux
and that is why on macOS,
sometimes you will find things
that work exactly the same on Linux.
So I have a directory,
my GitHub directory.
And in my GitHub directory,
I'm keeping projects for
all of my different courses.
Now, there is one file
that's a little bit special.
Let me show you.
Find . -name kube-setup
.sh.
That's a file that I'm
using in different courses
to help people set up
Kubernetes in an easy way.
As you can see, we find it six times here.
Now, the thing is that
I'm keeping this file
for a rapidly changing environment
and it does happen a lot
that I need to apply changes to the file.
Now, what do you think?
If I am going to change
one of these files,
how am I going to make sure
that all of the other files
that should have the exact same contents
do have the exact same contents?
Now, that is where a
hard link comes in handy.
So I've created one file.
I've created hard links
for everything else
and that means that if I modify,
no matter which one,
all of them are going
to change accordingly.
And that is how hard links can be useful.
Now that you can see
how I'm using hard links
in my own daily practice,
let's get back to Linux
and let me show you how
to manage hard links,
as well as symbolic links yourself.
Okay, I'm going to show
you ls -il on /etc/hosts.
I'm using the -i because -i for ls
is showing the inode number as well.
And we can see the inode
number listed first.
As you know, every file has a unique inode
and having insight in these inodes
is useful if you create links.
So I'm using ln /etc/hosts to myhosts.
And I'm using ls -il again,
now including myhosts.
And what do we see?
We see these files have the same inode
and the same other properties.
Now I'm using echo hello greater
than, greater than myhosts.
And what do we see?
Well, we see that they
still have the same inodes
and both of them have become bigger.
Both of them, relates to its two names,
pointing to the same file.
So you shouldn't even be
speaking about both of them.
Now let me use ln -s myhosts
to symhosts or whatever
you want to call it.
Now, using again ls -il
and I'm adding the symhosts,
and what do we see?
We see the nature of the symhosts.
Very dangerous.
Symbolic links, by default,
are pointing to a relative file name.
This relative file name
is really the contents
of the symbolic links.
Look, we have seven characters here
and it's not by coincidence
that the symbolic link has seven bytes.
That means that if you are going
to move your symbolic link,
you'll be in trouble.
Another thing that you
should see right here
is that the symbolic link
has obtained its own inode.
No permissions because the permissions
are set in the target file.
But I can use symhosts and symhosts
will give me access to the
modified file whatsoever.
Now, if I remove myhosts,
then what is going to happen?
Well, yes, I'm going to remove
and I'm going to cat
my symhosts and oh no,
no such file or directory.
Does that make sense?
It does because the symbolic
link has become invalid.
It's pointing to a file
that doesn't exist anymore.
Fortunately, it's very easy to recover
the original situation.
I just need to scroll up a little bit
to find the original ln command.
There we go.
And now my symhosts should be valid again.
As you can see, nothing is happening.
So the symbolic link only checks
to see if the target with
the name specified exists,
and as long as that is the case,
the symbolic link is happy.