- In this video, you will learn
how to use tar, the tape archiver.
So tar, as I said, is a tape archiver
and it was created a long time ago
when backups were still written to tape.
Nowadays, it doesn't and you
use it to compress files.
But in the original days,
when tar was created,
it didn't compress anything at all.
It was an archiving utility
or better, a tape streaming utility.
You can do so many things
with this tar utility
but the basic usage is
to compress or extract.
And you can use it to list
the contents of an archive.
So I have three different
command examples for you.
'tar -cvf', which will create an archive,
'tar -tvf', which will show the contents,
and 'tar -xvf', which extracts
the current directory.
By default extraction happens
to the current directory.
If you don't like it, you can use
minus uppercase C to
switch the output path.
And if you wanna use compression,
you can use '-z', '-j', or '-J'
depending on the compression
utility that you wanna use.
That's for Dzip, Bzip too or xz.
Let's go create some archives.
All right, so I am going to create
a couple of archives for you
and I want to apply
compression at the same time.
So I'm using 'tar -cvf'.
'c' is for create, 'v' is four verbose,
so that you will show what's happening,
and 'f' specifies the name of the archive.
So I'm calling it 'tmp/archive.tar'.
Next, I need to specify what
I wanna have in this archive.
Well, I wanna have '/home'
and '/etc' in there.
There we go.
And that was number one.
If I use 'ls -l/tmp/archive.tar'
when using 'ls-l' on this archive
we can see the size and
we can see it's quite big.
That's because nothing
has been compressed.
And I am going to do that right now
to start with by using the G Z utility.
G Z for Gzip.
If you want to use it,
use the '-z' option.
You can insert it anywhere
as long as it is not between the '-f'
and the name of the file
that you want to create.
Now, I'm also going to
change my extension.
I mentioned before that
extensions on Linux
don't really have a meaning.
But extensions make it easier
to see what is going on.
So T G Z is what's
commonly used for archives
that have been compressed
using the Gzip utility.
I'm going to change my command again
this time I'm making
the extension 'tar.bz2'
and I'm going to use lowercase J.
And now one more time,
so that we have seen all
the different compression solutions
and we can compare the results.
So I'm creating an X Z command this time
and we are using uppercase
J as a compression option.
Did you notice that it really
slows down at this point?
So it is X Z compression
engine is probably
not so very fast, but hopefully
we get something in return.
So now it'll be interesting to have a look
at 'ls- l /tmp/archive.t*'.
And here you can see the differences.
So what is the difference?
Well, X Z compression is twice
is good as Gzip compression
but it's also a lot slower.
That's all you need to know
about creation of the archives.
Now, two more commands,
because you might come across archives
that somebody has created
and you wanna know what's inside.
Then you use 'tar -tvf /tmp'
followed by the name of the archive.
Let's just use a tar archive.
It really doesn't matter
which one you are using
because tar recognizes compression,
will automatically extract.
Here we can see the contents,
and if you want to extract the file,
well then we are going
to make that 'tar -xvf'
and I can press enter.
And by pressing enter,
we can see the result.
And the result is that the archive
has been extracted to
the current directory.