- All right, in the previous video,
you've already seen how you
can use compression with tar,
but the compression utilities
are available as separate
utilities as well.
So, let's just list them.
The thing is that
there are so many compression
utilities available for Linux.
Each of them is a better combination
between time it takes
and compression ratio.
gzip, use -z in tar,
is still the most common
compression utility around.
And that is because the
results are quite convincing
and it's fast.
bzip2, use minus lowercase
j, is an alternative utility.
zip is sometimes used, not so very often,
but it's mainly used
because it is compatible to
the old Windows zip syntax.
Nowadays, the Windows
compression utilities
can also read Linux compress files.
So, that is why you hardly see
zip around on Linux anymore.
An xz or minus uppercase J
is showing up more often as well.
Most commonly used,
definitely gzip and xz.
The cool thing about xz is that
it's giving amazing results.
The cool thing about gzip
is that it's the fastest one around.
Choice is up to you.