- So, the first part is
to create an archive,
a compressed archive.
So, let's use tar czvf,
(computer keyboard clacking)
and I need to specify where to.
Well, I want to write
it to my home directory,
so let's call it lab6.tgz
and we are putting /etc and /opt in there.
Are you noticing anything
about this command?
Well, you should,
because I did not use a
hyphen in front of the options
and that's kind of funny.
There's a few commands on Linux,
tar and ps are the best
known of these commands,
that work with options with
as well as without a hyphen.
There's history behind it.
You just need to be aware
that if you see on the tar command
that somebody is not using their options,
well, it's just working.
Now we wanna know if this
worked out all right.
So let's use tar tvf
(computer keyboard clacking)
on lab6.tgz.
And there we can see it
is working perfectly.
Next we need to create a symbolic link
to the archive you've just
created in the tmp directory.
So the symbolic link must
be in the tmp directory.
So ln -s is how we create symbolic link,
lab6.tzg/tmp/lab6.link,
(computer keyboard clacking)
and then the question was
to remove the archive
from your home directory.
So rm lab6.tzg, and then
what happens to the link?
Well, ls -l on /tmp/lab6.link,
and we can see that the link is invalid.
The ls command is using convenient core,
so that it's easy to recognize
that this is an invalid link.
Otherwise, if you try to
access this /tmp/lab6.link,
(computer keyboard clacking)
no matter which command
you get a "no such file or directory".
That might be confusing about links
because sometimes you get
"no such file or directory",
but, "Hey, I see the file."
Yeah, but that's because it is a link.
Also notice in the output of ls,
the very first character all
the way to the left is an L,
and the L indicates that
this is a symbolic link.