- Before we get started
let's talk a bit about Linux.
Linux is an open source operating system
that is based on UNIX
and UNIX was the leading operating system
in the 1970s, 80s and 90s.
As UNIX was mainly used
for servers in companies,
expensive licenses needed to
be purchased for using it.
And by being open source, Linux
provides a free alternative
to UNIX, with the same look and feel.
Open source is a software
development model,
where the source code used
to compile software programs
is not proprietary and secret,
but accessible to anyone.
An open source has proved
to be very successful
as a development model,
as anyone can analyze
the source code and contribute to it.
Open source software
leads to free software
and that is free as in freedom of mind,
not as in free beer.
Companies can bundle open source software
which support licenses and
still charge for their product.
One major requirement
in open source software
is that most licenses
require the source code
to remain accessible to
everyone at all times.
But how about support?
Well, for use in companies,
support on software is essential
and support is available
at different levels.
You can think of help
if anything goes wrong
or support by hardware vendors
who will be able to help you
according to their support contracts
or support by application
vendors who will support
their main applications on top
of the supporting operating systems.
As you can guess, support is
essential for being successful
in an enterprise environment.
But Linux is free, and for that reason
it does not come with
support automatically,
because who owns it?
Well, that is where Enterprise
Linux distributions come in
like Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
And they differentiate themselves
by providing a support offering.
While working with Linux, there
are different distributions.
Linux itself is an operating
system that is made
from a software collection that includes
the Linux kernel, and
additional software components.
And the additional software
components are developed
as individual open source projects.
And you could gather all
the components yourself
and combine them into a
working operating system
but that's a lot of work.
And that is why Linux distributions
are doing that for you.
And they provide an
installer, a package manager
and other components to make it easy
to get started with Linux.
Now that you know a little bit
about the background of Linux,
let's talk about Red Hat Enterprise Linux.