- Now that we know about
the backgrounds of Linux,
let's talk about Red Hat
Enterprise Linux specifically.
Red Hat Enterprise Linux or RHEL
is the leading Linux distribution.
It started in 1993 as a Linux distribution
and it was amongst the first
to offer support for their software.
And because of the software offering,
Red Hat Enterprise Linux currently
is the most successful Linux distribution
for use in companies.
A new major version of RHEL
is released approximately every four years
and the current major
version of RHEL is nine.
During the live time of a major version,
minor updates are provided,
typically, in six to nine-month intervals,
but that depends if software requires it.
Big changes are introduced
only in major versions
and minor versions don't
see any big changes.
And while a new version
of RHEL is introduced,
the previous versions, normally,
are still supported for quite some time.
You can check this website
for the current RHEL support policy
because that tends to
change every now and then.