- Being open source, Red Hat
doesn't stand all by itself.
Red Hat participates in
many open source projects.
And one of these is Fedora
a free community distribution
that is sponsored by Red Hat.
Mature packages from Fedora
are included in CentOS stream
and CentOS stream is the
upstream project for RHEL ,
where community developers can participate
and contribute new software.
RHEL is derived from CentOS stream
and it offers an Enterprise
Linux distribution
which support options.
Rocky Linux And Alma Linux
are derived from Red Hat
Enterprise Linux as free
community alternatives.
Let's talk a bit about Fedora.
Fedora is a community project
which is sponsored by redhead.
The focus in Fedora is on the latest
and greatest developments
and not so much on stability.
Fedora has a 12 to 18 months life cycle
and no support options are available.
A new version is typically
released every six months
and Fedora is an awesome solution
if you want to be ahead
of the changes and run
Linux or modern hardware.
Then there is CentOS stream,
CentOS stream is extremely
important in the development life cycle
of RHEL, because it is the
upstream development platform.
And that means that new changes will occur
in CentOS stream before
being implemented in RHEL.
CentOS stream is based
on software that comes
from the Fedora project,
in which has reached a stable state.
And it has an expected
life cycle of five years.
Due to its ever evolving
nature, CentOS to stream is not
a recommended distribution to use
in production environments.
And then there is RHEL, RHEL
is Red Hat Enterprise Linux
which is a supported Linux
distribution that is offered
for used by organizations.
It has a life cycle of 10 years.
And it offers support on the software.
It integrates in the
Red Hat product family,
where additional expertise,
security, certification,
and monitoring can be offered
through different products.
You can also use it unsupported for free,
up to 16 instances of Red Hat
Enterprise Linux are available
through developer.RedHat.com
Then there are also Rocky
Linux and Alma Linux,
which will be considered
part of the Red Hat family.
Before 2019, CentOS was a
free alternative to Red Hat
Enterprise Linux, where all
Red Hat proprietary elements
were removed.
And nowadays, CentOS stream has
become the only version
of CentOS and it serves
as an upstream for RHEL.
So the old way that CentOS was
used does not exist anymore.
Rocky Linux was created as
an answer by the original
founders of the CentOS project
who thought that the
free Red Hat alternative
should be available.
Alma Linux had the same idea in mind,
and Alma was created by cloud Linux.
But, as Red Hat offer up to
16 instances of RHEL for free,
the need for free distributions
like Alma and Rocky is not
as big as it used to be.
Now let's talk a bit about RHEL versions.
Red Hat Enterprise Linux is a foundation
for some other products as well.
Like a Red Hat CoreOS
which is an image based
container host that is used
in OpenShift environments.
Or Red Hat universal based image,
or UBI, which is a subset of
RHEL packages that can be used
as a foundation for building
custom container images.
Now that you know about
the backgrounds of RHEL
let's talk about how to get it.