- All right, so now that
we know a little bit
about the background of
Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
let's talk about how to get it.
Supported and paid for
instances of RHEL are offered
through redhat.com or
the partner ecosystem.
That means you need to buy
it before getting it there,
but there's also
unsupported developer access
to many Red Hat products
through developers.redhat.com.
And that is what I recommend
that you use for this course.
So as a developer, but really
as anyone you can run up
16 instances of RHEL for free.
You do not have to be a developer.
Nobody is checking if you are a developer.
If you just wanna learn
Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
you can use the developers
account as well.
As an alternative there's
also one free evaluation copy
of RHEL that can be obtained
through access.redhat.com.
But really there's no reason to use it
because you can get it for for free
on developers.redhat.com.