- All right.
So here we are on developers.redhat.com.
And in order to get
access, you need to log in.
So here we have the login to
your Red Hat account window.
Enter your account credentials
or you create a new account
using register for Red Hat account.
Also, you can use either of these options
like LinkedIn and Twitter
and Facebook and GitHub
as an external authentication
provider and login with that.
And then you click next.
So next, you enter your password.
You click login, and that
should give you access.
And, oh, here we can see
that Red Hat requires a
little bit more information.
These are privacy related settings.
So select whatever you want
and continue with that.
So now, I am logged in,
and I can start using.
So, we need to go to the products.
And in the products, there
is Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
And in Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
you can just click
download RHEL 9 for free.
So you click it.
So after clicking,
you can see all the
downloads that are available.
And what you wanna have, well,
it's typically the big one
which is right here, the
X86_64, eight gigabytes,
ISO image, that contains all
the software that you need.
Notice that these images
are for different platforms.
Most people probably need X86_64.
Alternatively, if that doesn't work
because of platform computability issues,
you can select AARCH64.
This is just about the
supporting platform,
the computing platform
that you are going to use.
It doesn't change anything in
the functionality of Linux.
So click download,
it'll start downloading.
And once it is done,
you are good to continue
and start installing it.