- In this video, I'll
tell you about ownership.
Ownership is very important
in Linux permissions.
And that is because
ownership is the first thing
to determine which permissions a user has.
Every file has a user-owner, a group-owner
and the others entity,
that is also granted permissions.
We refer to that as ugo.
Ugo for user group and others.
Linux permissions are not additive.
If you're the owner,
permissions are applied and that's all.
So, when you are the owner,
nobody looks at the
permissions that you got
from possible group membership.
You can use ls-l to
display current ownership
and associated permissions.
And as the best practice,
if you are going to set permissions,
first set ownership.
And then you modify permissions.
That makes it easier to keep the overview
of what you are doing.