- In this video, I will tell you
how to change file ownership.
It's pretty simple.
There are two commands involved.
First command is chown,
for change owner.
Chown needs a username
and optionally can use
a group name as well.
And next it needs a file name.
And that allows you to set the ownership.
C H G R P is what you do
to set group ownership
but you can also use chown
to set user ownership as well
as group ownership.
Let me show you.
So to demonstrate this
I'm going to create a directory.
Let's call it data new files.
I'm creating this
directory as the root user.
If I type ID, always a convenient command
If you work with permissions,
then you can see my
current user ID is zero.
My current group ID is zero as well.
Because of these current settings
the ownership will be set accordingly.
So as you can see new files as user root
as the user owner group
root as the group owner.
And right here, starting the
second position up to the end,
we can see the permissions
that are currently applied.
So read, write, execute,
read, execute, read, execute,
which means that the user
has read write execute,
the group has read, execute and others,
which is everybody else, as
read and execute as well.
Now, the purpose
of this demo is to show you
how to use chown and C H D R P.
So chown can be used as follows.
If I use chown Lisa on new files,
then the result is that user Lisa is now
user owner of the files.
If you change ownership
that doesn't affect the
permissions at all,
it's a separate setting.
So you will need to change
the permissions accordingly,
If that is needed.
Also convenient to say
you can use something like
chown Linda colon sales
on new files.
In which the colon is a separator
between the user and the group.
Now, if we check the current
permission assignments
we can see the user Linda
and group sales is set as a group owner.
Now, alternatively, you can use C H G R P.
So let me use C H G R P.
I don't have that many groups,
so let me use wheel as a group to make
that the group owner.
Notice that normally
you would never do that,
but I just need a group to
make that the owner and really, I don't
like group wheel being the
owner of new files because wheel
should really be used
for pseudo purposes only.
So, you know what
let me use yet another
alternative chown colon sales
on new file and the result is
what you can see right here.
User Linda as well as group sales
are owner of the directory new files.