- In this video,
I will give you an overview
of the basic permissions.
They are read, write and execute.
Now, these permissions
have different meaning
if applied to files or directories.
So if you have read on a file
then the result is that well,
how surprising you can read the file
or let's call it open the file.
If you have read on directories,
so it's a little bit different.
That permission allows you to list files
in the directory.
Read on the directory
is not about reading
files in the directory,
it just allows you to
read the list of files
that is inside the directory.
The other permission is write.
And if you have write on a file
and you are allowed to modify
the contents of a file.
Write on the directory
allows you to create
or to delete files.
It's pretty easy to understand
if you know that the directory
is really just a list of files,
write on the directory
allows you to modify
that list of files.
Now, we have execute on files.
Very important permission,
execute or file allows
you to run the file.
And execute on the directory,
allows you to use cd, change directory
to get inside the directory.
There's one more thing
that we need to know
about these permissions
and that is the so-called octal modes.
For read that will be 4.
For write that will be the 2.
And for execute that will be 1.
I'll tell you all about
that in just a little bit.
One special permission
that we need to talk
about is x, special X.
So also special about x.
When x for execute is
applied to recursively,
it would make directories
as well as files executable.
And that's not good
because you don't want
files to become executable
in an uncontrolled way.
That should always be a
very conscious decision.
Now, in recursive commands,
you should use uppercase X.
Instead, we call that special X.
If you use uppercase X,
then directories will be
granted the execute permissions,
but files will only get
the execute permission
if it is set already
elsewhere on the file.
And that's a pretty simple,
but good protection of your files.
To avoid that they will become
executable unexpectedly.
In an next video,
I'll show you how to set permissions.