- In this video, I'll show you
how to manage basic permissions.
First, let's have a look at the commands.
So we have chmod, for change mode,
change mode is used to manage permissions.
No matter which permissions,
chmod is always what you are going to use
and you can use it in either the absolute
or the relative mode.
In the absolute mode, you use digits
to refer to the permissions
you want to set.
So chmod 750 on myfile.
In the 750, the seven relates to the user,
the five relates to the
group and the zero to others.
Now seven, seven is
four plus two plus one,
which means that user is
getting read, write and execute.
Group has five, that's four plus one.
So group has read and execute
and others has nothing.
There's also the relative mode
and the relative mode is convenient
if you want to apply an
individual permission to file.
Let's go check this out.
All right.
So let's get back to
the permission settings.
We have this new files directory.
Now, what do we see on
the new files directory?
We see that the owner has seven
and group others have five, five.
I don't like that very much.
So the easiest way to change it is
by using chmod 750 on new files.
So that was easy.
Now, if you want to
change that, you can use
chmod followed by G+W on new files.
And the result is that at this point,
the group also has the right permission.
And the chmod command,
I have used G plus W,
you can probably guess
what the possibilities are.
U, G and O, as I said, UGO,
for user group and others.
So if I would do chmod O+W for instance,
not that that makes sense,
there we can see that
others has right permissions
but that's not a good idea.
So let me do chmod O minus
W on new files as well.
Right, there's one more thing
that I want to show you.
So let's go check it out.
We have this user, and let's
do this for user Linda.
Okay, let me show you
the current permissions.
LS minus LD dot.
These are the permissions on
user Linda home directory.
Only user Linda has permissions
on the home directory.
Nobody else.
I am going to use touch rootfile.
Why can I do that?
Well, that's because
I'm doing it as a root
and a root is living in a world
where permissions don't apply.
Permissions are for ordinary
users, not for root.
Here we can see that the
root file has been created.
Now the interesting
thing, if I open a file
as user Linda, and I check
in my current home directory,
I can see this file.
Now, the question is, is
this command going to work?
So can user Linda remove
this file, yes or no?
You have any idea, let's check it out.
She can, and I bet you
are surprised about it,
because on a rootfile, you can see
that well root is owner,
root is group owner
and others has agreed permissions only.
That may be correct, but don't forget
that deleting a file
requires right permissions
on the directory.
This is Linda's home directory
and on the home directory,
user Linda has read,
write and execute, so she can
delete anything she wants.