- In this video, I want to tell you
how to configure shared group directories.
So what is the thing?
Well, if members of the same
group need to share files
within a directory, some special
permissions are required.
The shared group ID
permission, also known as SGID,
ensures that all files created
in the shared group directory
are group owned by the group
owner of the directory.
The sticky bit permission
ensures that only the user
who is either owner of the file
or of the directory
that contains the file,
is allowed to delete the file.
So how does it work?
Well, we have chmod g+s,
which will apply SGID,
or chmod +T, which assigns sticky bit.
And if you want to use absolute mode
of four digit number is used,
of which the first digit is
for the special permissions,
as in chmod 3770, which will grants SGID
and sticky bit, as well
as rwx for user and group.
Let me show you.
All right, so I want to show you
what's going on, LS
minus L, what do we have?
We have these profs and these students
so we should be working
with the profs directory.
So if I use ID on user Anna,
we can see user Anna is a member of profs
and likewise for Audrey,
also a member of profs.
So I am going to open a shell as user Anna
and to the directory data profs.
And I am going to create
a couple of files.
That should be enough, in LS minus L.
And what do we see?
We see that all of these files
are group owned by user Anna.
That's not what I wanted.
We need these to be group
owned by the group profs,
not the group Anna.
So what are we going to do about it?
Well, we are going to apply, set group ID.
Before doing that, there's another thing
that I want you to be aware of.
I'm opening a shell as user
Audrey, and if this user
goes to data profs, then what do we find?
Couple of files.
What do you think, is Audrey
allowed to remove files?
Well, the answer is yes,
because Audrey is a member
of the group profs and group profs
has right on the directory.
And with right on the directory,
you can remove, easy like that.
Let's go fix it, so how do we fix?
Well simple, chmod 3770 /data/profs.
So right now we can see that
the permissions have changed.
How do we see that?
We see that the position
where before we had X
or group execute, we now
have S, lowercase S indicates
that we have set group ID
as well as group execute.
And we have uppercase D, uppercase D,
which is for the sticky bit.
So that means that if I am
logging in as user Anna again
and I go to that directory
and I create a new file,
then on this new file,
we have the group profs automatically set
as the group owner.
Now, how about we log
in as user Audrey again
and try to delete a file.
I mean, you do want to check
if it's working out all right, don't you?
So SU minus Audrey,
back to the data profs directory, and RM
minus F star and oh,
Audrey is getting operation not permitted.
And that's what sticky is doing.