- In this video,
I will tell you how to
apply default permissions.
So, in order to understand
default permissions,
we need the umask.
The umask is a shell setting
that subtracts the umask
from default permissions.
The default is set in etc/bashrc.
And if you want to set a
specific umask for a user,
you can always put that
in the .bashrc file
in the user home directory.
Now, in order to understand the umask,
you should know that default permissions
for files are 666, and
for directories are 777.
So how does that work?
Well, let's imagine that
you have a umask of 027.
Now, you do the subtraction.
027 on 666, means that
you have 640 remaining.
Because six minus zero is still six.
Six minus two is four.
And six minus seven, well,
that will be minus one,
but we can't do minus.
So zero will be the remaining thing.
On directories, default
permissions are set to 777.
And in case you are wondering why,
well, the difference between
the six and the seven
is the execute permission.
And on directories, to do
something that is useful,
you always need execute permission.
So 027 on the directory
will result in 750,
so that the user can do
anything, the group can read,
and others can do nothing at all.
Let me show you how this umask works.
So the nice thing about umask
is that it is a shell setting.
So I'm typing umask, and here
we can see the current umask.
As you can see, it's a four digit umask.
Please ignore the first digit
because that relates to
the special permissions
that we just talked about,
and you will never ever change it.
So, let's just consider this to be 022.
Now, what is the result?
The result is that if
Linda creates a file,
the permissions are set to
read, write, read, read.
Now I am going to change that umask 027.
And now if I type umask again,
we can see that it's
automatically applied to 027.
And if Linda creates another file,
then this other file has the
new permissions assigned.
Now, I just typed it in a shell
and it makes it nonpersistent.
You want it to be persistent.
You need to put it in the .bashrc.
And in the .bashrc, you can see
that this is a shell script,
but if you put it somewhere near the end
of the shell script, then
there's nothing wrong with it.
So if I use umask 077,
that's something that the user can do.
Then, at the moment that the
user is opening a new shell
or logging in again, then the
new umask will be applied.
A quick trick to activate these settings
is by sourcing it using .space.bashrc.
The dot command is a source command,
and that'll make sure that its settings
are applied immediately.
As you can see right now, it's 077.
And that ensures that everything
that user Linda is creating
is visible for you.
So Linda only.
That's how you can use the umask.