- All right, in order to do this lab,
we need to do two things.
Well in the lab, I'm
reading default permissions.
And as I read default permissions,
I think before we do
anything it's a good idea
to start with the default permissions.
These default permissions
should apply to all users.
So etc bashrc is what we need.
Now, if you are going
to modify etc bashrc,
then you need to be very careful
to do it in the right location.
In etc bashrc, we can see that umask
is set by some shell script.
Now this might be a little bit too much
to understand all the way by
yourself but I can explain.
If the user ID is greater than 199,
then we set umask to 002.
And else, we set umask to 022.
What does that mean?
Well, effectively it
means that ordinary users
have the umask 002.
The root user has the umask 022.
And if I want to change
that, I can do it right here.
I make that umask 007.
So that ensures that any
file that the user creates
is a readable, writeable, and executable,
if that applies to the
user, as well as the group,
and others has no access at all.
So then the other part of
the lab, for this other part,
we need two directories,
mkdir -p/data/profs.
And we need mkdir -p/data for students.
You remember the minus P option
is creating the entire path
and that allows you to create
a sub directory structure,
even if the parent
directly does not exist.
Now we need to apply some changes here.
So if you read it,
create a shared group directory structure,
we just did that.
That meets the following requirements.
Members of the groups have
full read and write access
to their directories and others
have no permissions at all.
That's pretty simple.
Chgrp-profs on profs and
Chgrp students on students.
And let's students with an S.
Let's verify using ls -l.
We can see that the
permissions are said correctly
and now we can use chmod
770 on these directories.
We need to do that for students,
as well as for the profs directory.
And let's verify using ls -l
and there we can see that
everything is looking all right.
So the profs and the students
are owners of that directory.
Others is no business
being in that directory.
And in case you're wonder
about the user owner,
well, the user owner we really
don't care about user owner
because that is a root
and you know the root
user has access anyway.
So if the question was
phrased like this on the exam
then I would say, if they don't
ask anything about the user
just don't touch it, keep it as it is,
it'll be good.