- Before we can talk
about root privileges.
We need to understand the root user.
Since the earliest days of UNIX,
a user account with UID 0 existed
to perform administration tasks.
And on Linux, this user by
default has the name root.
The special thing about
a root user is that
the root user operates in kernel space.
And for that reason has unlimited access
to all parts of the system.
We call root also the unrestricted user
or the privileged user.
There are no limitations
in the original design
of the UNIX operating
system for the root user.
Now, RHEL 9, it's up to you
to define what you want to do with root.
You can decide whether or
not to activate this user.
And if the user root is not activated
the administrative user is
used for administration access.
And this administrative user is the user
that you need to create.
While installing RHEL 9,
if you don't have a root user,
'cause otherwise your
system would be unmanageable
and that's not good.
If you want to activate the root user,
you just have to set a password.
We have seen that while installing RHEL 9.
But from a security perspective,
it may be a good idea not
to have an active root user at all.
Additional measures are possible
to restrict the root user
access to the system.
For instance, also during the
installation, you can decide
whether or not the root user
is allowed to use secure shell
or SSH to connect to a server.
And I can tell you by default
the root user cannot RHEL 9.