- The su command is used
to switch user accounts
from a shell environment.
And you can use the su
command with a - option,
which allows you to load
the complete environment
of the target user as well.
And while using su, the password
of the target user is entered.
And if the root user has a password
you can use su - or su on a root as well.
Using su - to open a root shell
is considered bad practice
however, use sudo -i instead.
The main benefit of sudo -i
is that nobody has to know
the the root password, and
it's for authorized uses only,
that makes it more secure.
What is convenient about su,
is that you can also use it for
testing other user accounts.
And that is something that
we are going to do a lot
in the next couple of lessons.
As administrator, you create a user,
you assign some permission,
you wanna test use su -
to figure out if it works out as expected.
Let's do a quick demo.
So here I am in a shell
as my ordinary user
I'm using su - anna, it's
prompting for a password.
Whose password would that be?
Password of the target user,
su is always prompting for the
password of the target user.
That means that if you
are an ordinary user
and you want to use su a lot,
you need to know lots of passwords.
But at this moment I have a subshell
and in that subshell and
whoami is going to prove it,
my user identity is Anna.
Using exit to get back
to the student shell,
and then we are all done.
Now if I use su - as mentioned,
it's always recommended
to use a minus with su.
It's prompting for a password, again,
this time the password of the root user.
As you can see I'm in a root shell.
Now the fun thing is that
user root can su into anybody.
So if root would use su - anna,
root is not prompted
for a password at all.
And that is what makes su convenient.
If you have administrative privileges
and you want to test access rights
for specifics users this is the way to go.