- In this video, I will
tell you about sudo.
So sudo is a much more secure mechanism
to perform administrative tasks.
Behind sudo is the /etc/sudoers
configuration file.
And while editing
/etc/sudoers through visudo,
very detailed administrator
privileges can be assigned.
In SU it's all or nothing,
you're in a root shell
or you're not.
In sudo it is possible to assign
this one or two commands to
a user that can be performed
at administrative
privileges and nothing else.
Now, if a user has sudo privileges,
to learn an administration task using sudo
the user needs to type sudo
followed by the command.
And that will prompt for
the current user password.
And it'll run the command
if this is allowed through etc/sudoers
and if not it'll print
a fine error message.
To open a root shell, sudo-i can be used.
Now let me show you.
Now let's look at this.
I'm in a shell as user Anna
and I'm using sudo LS/root.
That's a test that I like a lot.
It's non intrusive, not dangerous at all,
but it proves if it is working.
Here, we can see what's happening
when a user is typing sudo.
User needs to prompt
password, so here we go.
Password for user Anna
and Anna is not in the sudo as well.
The incident will be reported.
That is what is so secure about sudo.
Now, if I exit and exit again,
to get back in my student shell,
and I do the same sudo LS/root
then we can see that it is working.
And that is
because the student user
is the administrative user.
The first user that you have created
after installing of your system
will always have sudo privileges.
And this already demonstrates why sudo
is much better than SU
for performing administration task.
But there's so much more
that you can do with sudo.
In the next video, I'll
tell you more about it.