- Behind sudo, there's
a lot of configuration
that can be done.
And this configuration is
in the file etc/sudoers.
First thing to know, do not
edit this file directly.
You can only edit it using visudo.
That's because visudo is
doing a couple of check
so making sure that
everything is going all right.
And there's another way.
Instead of editing the
configuration file directly,
you can also consider
creating drop-in-files
in /ect.sudoers.d.
/ect.sudoers is installed from packages
and it may be overwritten
and drop in files will
never be overwritten.
We've seen that before,
and this is something
that is commonly done
in Linux environment.
Before we have seen it
in etc profile and etc profile.d.
You wanna keep your changes,
store them somewhere else.
That's the message.
Now let's talk about using sudo
to provide administrator access.
Users who are a member of the group wheel,
get full sudo access.
And that is accomplished
by including the line %wheel is All=(ALL)
ALL in /etc/sudoers.
If you need a user to have this full level
of sudo privileges,
you should consider using
usermod -aG wheel myuser,
where myuser is the user and -aG wheel
is making the user member of that group.
Make sure you use
lowercase a, uppercase G,
because otherwise it doesn't work.
More about this in the next lesson,
do not enable the line, %wheel
is All=(ALL) NOPASSWD: ALL,
I mean it's convenient and
it's nice that that line exists
as a default example, but
it's also very dangerous
because it'll provide full sudo access
without entering a password,
that is like having a root
user without password.
Just don't do it.
If you don't like entering
your user password
every five minutes,
increase authentication
token expiration by adding the following.
Defaults
timestamp_type=global,timestamp_timeout=60.
What is that doing?
Well when you use sudo, you
are prompted for a password,
at that moment, a token will be generated
and that token will be cashed in the cash
of your local, and it is
valid for five minutes.
If you use this parameter,
your token will be valid
for a much longer period.
So if you want it to be valid for an hour
until you type your
password again, use this.
Notice by the way that
this is not something
you'll have to do on RHCSA,
it's just something I need you to know
to make your systems more secure.
You can also use sudo to provide access
to specific tasks, in order to do so,
you can use drop-in flies,
like Lisa ALL=/sbin/useradd,
/usr/bin/passwd,
which allows user Lisa to add
users and to set passwords.
You can consider using command arguments
to make the commands more specific.
What do you think for instance
of
%users
ALL=/bin/mount/dev/sdb,/bin/umount/dev/sdb,
which allows all members
of the group users
to mount, but only the device SDB
or what do you think
of Linda
ALL=/usr/bin/passwd,!/usr/bin/passwd root.
And that last one is one example
that I would like to show you.
All right, I'm using
sudo vim /etc/sudoers.d,
Linda and in there, I
am going to add Linda,
ALL=/usr/bin/pasawd.
Let's imagine that Linda
is a help desk user
and you wanna make sure that user Linda
is allowed to reset passwords.
One requirement, we do
need user Linda to exist.
So sudu useradd Linda
and sudo passwd Linda,
to give the user a password as well.
So now we need to open a as user Linda,
that's where SU comes in.
SU - Linda opens the shell.
I need to provide the
password for the target user.
And there we go. sudo passwd
Anna, she's going to work.
We don't know it yet, but
here we can see it's working,
changing password for user Anna.
Typing the password once,
typing the password twice.
So isn't that nice?
Now Linda looks to be an
innocent help desk user,
but what do you think of this,
sudo passwd root, changing
password for user root.
Something is not right here
and what is not right is,
well basically, the way
how this has been applied.
Let's get back to the sudo file,
in this sudo file, we
can see that user Linda
has the the permissions
to use usr/bin/passwd.
So Linda can use this
command for any user.
Now, in order to make it more secure,
I'm going to add !/usr/bin/passwd root.
Can you guess what this is doing?
Let's check it out, back to the Linda,
and as user Linda,
user Linda is not allowed
to execute bin/passwd root,
as root on localhost.localdomain.
So what did we just do?
Well, we just created an exception.
User Linda is allowed to run passwd,
but not for user root.
The funny thing here
is that you might think
that the exception comes
before the generic rule.
That's not the case.
You first put the generic rule,
then you put the exception
and then you're done.