- In this video, we'll talk
about Secure Shell or SSH,
which can be used login you remotely.
By default, all RHEL servers
run a Secure Shell server.
You can use systemctl to verify.
Systemctl is a part of systemd,
the manager of everything about
which I will tell you later.
Systemctl status sshd should
show you that SSH is running.
And SSH access is also allowed
through the firewall by default.
No need to do anything here.
Notice that root access is often denied.
It is in fact denied by default on RHEL9.
So by default, you cannot
SSH into remote servers.
If you want to SSH to
connect to a remote server
you need to find out a couple of things.
First, use "ip a" to find the IP address
of the remote server.
And then you can use SSH
followed by the IP address
which will connect to this IP address
using your current user account.
If you don't want to use
your current user account
that's also okay,
just use ssh username at IP address.
And that will connect
you as a specific user.
Let's go check this out.
So to start with, I'm
showing you sudo systemsctl,
status sshd, and now we can
see that the sshd is running
and it's running as it should be.
For now, that's enough.
Now, ssh is for connecting
to remote server.
In fact, I don't have a
remote server here yet.
So, I'm using "ip a",
and I'm going to pretend
that this is a remote server.
What I'm looking for here
is the IP address that is shown by "ip a."
And I am going to use SSH 192.168.29.211,
which is doing what?
It's opening the SSH session.
So, while doing so it receives
an SSH key fingerprint
from the remote server.
And you need to store that
in your local environment
so that the next time you
can verify the authenticity
of the remote server,
then you enter the password
for the remote user
and up, you're in.
Once you are done in your
SSH session, you type "exit"
and you are back on the ordinary server.
Now, let's do this one more time
but this time specifying
a username, root@.
So, it's prompting for the
password of this user root.
And what do we get?
We get nothing.
Is that expected behavior?
Yes, that is expected behavior,
because if you don't specifically
enable root SSH access
or RHEL9, route SSH access will be denied.