- All right, so here we
have the lab solution.
I'm going to continue a bit
on what we have already
done for user linda.
So sudo vim on /etc/sudoers.d/linda
where we have ALL=/usr/bin/passwd
not usr/bin/passwd root,
and let's just include these
other commands as well.
/usr/sbin/useradd, and /usr/sbin/usermod,
and /usr/sbin/userdel.
(computer keyboard clacking)
So that should do it for
the part of user linda.
Now, I also wanna do a sudo visudo.
This visudo is very convenient
because it's a default
sudo configuration file
and it contains nice examples.
Go all the way down,
and if you go all the way down,
you see some example lines
like this one right here,
which is, oh boy, very bad line.
Same thing without the password.
Honestly, I don't get it,
why they keep it as an example by default.
It's like inviting people,
like, "Hey, you wanna do
something very stupid? Go ahead.
"You only have to remove
the comment line from it."
So let's just clean that up.
I like this one as well
because this one is giving you an example
of what we need to do for user linda,
in case you don't remember it.
And you know on your RHCSA exam,
it's so useful if you can
find examples like this.
And I am going to put in generic defaults.
time stamp_type is global,
(computer keyboard clacking)
and timeout is, well,
what do you want it to be?
Let's do 60, 60 sounds
reasonable, and let's save this.
And uh-oh! What do we see?
We see we did something invalid,
and that's what good about visudo.
So it's asking what now?
I'm pressing enter because
I wanna know my choices.
I am going to edit my sudoers file again,
and that is bringing me to the line
that contains the problem,
and the problem is that
we need timestamp_timeout.
You could have guessed
that because just timeout,
what is just timeout?
It's a timestamp_timeout.
Now I'm saving the changes again,
and now you can see that sudo is happy.
So once more, su - linda to
open a shell as user Linda.
and as user linda I'm
using sudo useradd bob.
And of course it's prompting
for the password for user Linda,
and well, it's not
complaining about anything,
so that seems to be happening all right.
Sudo passwd bob, that's still allowed.
Still allowed, and Bob is
getting a password right now.
And that's all you needed
to do for this lab.