- Hello, and welcome to Lesson 5.
In this lesson, you'll
learn about the Bash shell,
the command interpreter on Linux.
This lesson is about different
features that it offers
to make working on the
command line easier.
You'll learn how to work
with redirection and piping
as well as history.
Next, I'll show you some
convenient keyboard shortcuts
that will make working
with the shell easier.
Then you'll learn about shell expansion,
special characters, variables,
and the alias command.
And in the end, I will show you
how to tune the best environment
using the different configuration files.
At the end of this lesson,
you'll find a lab as
well as the lab solution.