- In this video, I will tell you
about some of the most essential features
of the Bash Shell, I/O
redirection, as well as piping.
So, what is this about?
Well, redirection uses
what we call the STDIN,
STDERR and the STDOUT,
which are standard input, standard error
and standard output to work
with command input and output
in a flexible way.
You can use the greater-than
sign to write the result
of a command to a file.
Or a double greater-than
sign to append the result
into a file.
Or 2 greater-than to write
the standard error messages
to somewhere like a
special device, dev null,
which is the discard device
you will never see it back.
Or you can use smaller-than to
fetch the input from a file.
The other option is piping.
In piping, the standard output
of the first command is
used as standard input
of the second command.
Let me show you.
So, if I'm typing a command like ls,
then the ls command is writing its output
to the standard output.
Standard input, standard
output, standard error
is normally the combination
of your keyboard and your screen.
So, we can see the output on screen.
Now, if I use ls greater-than output,
then it redirects the
standard output to a file.
The file will be created
and the name of the file is output.
So, I can use cat to check the contents
of the file and there
we can see that the list
of files that ls is
normally showing is now
in the file output.
Now, if I do this again,
who greater-than output,
then what is going to happen?
Well, let me use cat to show you.
We can see that the contents
of the file has been overwritten.
If you use a greater-than sign
and the file already exists,
the file will be overwritten
with a new output.
And that's why we have the append mode.
So, ls greater-than, greater-than output.
The double greater-than is appending.
And now if I use cat on
my output file again,
there we can see the
result of the who command
is still there.
And you can also see the
result of the new command.
Now, 2 greater-than is what
you can use to redirect errors.
Let me do ls on something
that does not exist.
There we go.
I'm getting an error message.
Now, this error message
is quite convenient,
but later we will find
examples of commands generating
so many error messages
that don't make sense,
that you might want to redirect them
to the discard device, dev null.
And in order to redirect
your standard output,
2 greater-than is what
you are going to use.
That means that you will
only see the regular output.
That is maybe easier to see
if we use 2 arguments to ls,
a non-existing file and an existing file.
And as you can see, we
don't see the error,
we do see the name of the existing file.
The smaller-than sign is
not so very important.
You are not going to use that very often.
It's for input redirection.
The thing is, you could
very well use something
like cat smaller-than output
to do input redirection.
But the thing is that
the input redirection
for most commands also works
without the smaller-than sign.
And that's why this one
is not very important.
Now, let's have a look at piping.
Well, in fact, we already
have seen piping in man -k,
man -k user pipe grep 8
was doing what?
Well, it's producing output.
So, man -k user is producing output
and it's sending this
output to the grep command.
And grep is filtering all
lines containing an 8.
You can do that once.
You can do that even more times.
So, first you grep,
then you do another pipe
and you send it to less to
see the results page by page.
This piping is extremely
powerful in Linux environments
because it's exactly
what the Linux philosophy
is all about.
In the Linux philosophy it's
all about using commands
that are very powerful or very
strong in what they are doing
but not very feature-rich.
Why are these commands
not very feature-rich?
Well simple, because you can
use a pipe to apply the feature
using some other command.
Let's see it this way.
Why don't we use
man -k
user -8, for instance.
Well, there's no need to program
a filtering option in man
because in Linux we have grep
and there's no more powerful filtering
than the grep command.