- In this video, I will tell you about
another great of the feature bash shell.
History.
So, bash registers recently used commands
and you can type history for an overview.
Now, the commands that
are stored in history
are kept in a file,
which is in the home directory till this
the home directory and
the name of the file
is .bash_history.
And that makes them
available beyond sessions.
So once you log out,
you restart your server,
you can still access
your previous history.
The size of the history
is set by two variables,
HISTSIZE and HISTFILESIZE.
By default they are set to 1000
and that means that if you are not doing
very much on the Linux shell
you might even find commands
that you've used a year ago.
Now history is convenient,
but what it's all about is to
repeat commands from history.
There are different ways to
You can use the up arrow
to easily repeat commands
by scrolling backwards.
You can also use Control R
which performs a reverse search
based on the pattern that you've entered.
Or !nn where NN is the number.
This will repeat a command
from history based on its number.
And !a repeats the last command
that starts with the letter A.
Before, moving on, let me show you.
So here we have the history command
and as you can see, I have
used 63 commands already.
Now I can use my arrow key and scroll up
and repeat commands.
I can also use exclamation
mark command number.
And in fact, I like this
exclamation mark command number
because that allows me to repeat
a command very specifically.
Alternatively, you can use
control R, the reverse I search.
So if I'm searching on user,
now you can see that on my prompt
I automatically get the last
command that had user in it.
So I'm pressing Enter on
it and then I repeat it.
Now, repeating commands
from history is nice
but the fact that everything
is stored in history
is not always that convenient.
Let's talk a little bit more about that.
So every now and then you
need to manage history
and there are a couple
of commands involved.
History -w synchronizes current history
from memory to the history file.
Normally your history is
synchronized if you log out
or if you exit your shell properly.
But if you wanna make sure
that you keep important modifications
it doesn't hurt using history -w
so that if one minute
later your server crashes
you still have your history.
History -c clears your
current history, all of it.
And if you really want
to remove everything
then you should not forget
to also use history -w
to commit this to the history file.
Much more convenient
and this is something
that you are probably
going to use a lot is history
-d followed by a line number.
This will remove the specific
line from current history.
Let me show you.
So here we have the history command
and I think command number
56 did not make sense.
So I'm using !56.
Well, no, I don't want
to keep that command
so I'm using history -d on 56.
And now if I'm using history again,
now, what do we see?
We see that the previous LS
whatever has been removed.
And hey, just a detail, if
it's really that important,
we should also repeat 66
which has the same command.
Again, be careful to remove whatever
you want to remove using history -d
but history -d definitely is convenient
especially if you have typed
your password by accident
then it's stored in history as well.
Now there's one little thing,
if I open a second tab in my terminal
and I type history in this
second tab, then what do we see?
And as you can see, we don't have
the 60 something commands
from my other terminal,
this is only a limited number of commands.
Now, if I type echo hello world
and then I get back to my first
terminal and I use history,
do I see echo hello world?
Well, the answer is no
because normally history is kept
local to your terminal session.
There are two ways to write your history,
history -w or if you
just close your terminal
the decent way by typing exit,
then your history is merged as well.
Notice that right now I see
69 commands in my history.
And right now, oh, it's still 69 commands
that did not change anything.
Well I'm going to exit this terminal.
And now I'm going to
enter my terminal again.
And once more, history,
and what do we see?
78 commands.
That's because the two
histories have now been merged,
they've been written to the history file.
This is something that you
should definitely remember
if you have multiple
terminals that you work from
your history might be saved out of order.
And this is how you can work
even if your history
is saved out of order.