- The BASH shell is providing a number
of very useful keyboard shortcuts,
they really make your work easier.
Let's have a look.
To start with there's Control + C
which quits the current
interactive process.
If you're getting stuck in some command
and it doesn't want to
move, try Control + C.
There's also Control + D,
Control + D sends an end-of-file character
to the current interactive process.
It might not always be clear
when to use Control + C, Control + D.
My suggestion is just try,
one of them will work.
Control + A, you've seen
me doing it a couple
of times already.
It moves your cursor to the start
of the current line and that allows you
to add commands to the current line.
Or Control + E which moves the cursor
to the end of the current line.
We have talked about Control + R
which is the reverse search in history.
We have not yet talked about Control + L
which clears your screen
so that you don't see any
previous commands anymore.
Control + U is also convenient,
it removes the current line.
And then there are a couple
of keyboard shortcuts
that allows you to move between words.
Like Alt B, which moves the
cursor one word backward.
The last keyboard shortcut
I wanna talk about is Alt F,
which moves the cursor
one, one word forward
can be quite convenient as well.
Let me show you how this works.
So here we have my screen
with lots of commands.
I'm using Control + L to wipe it.
And now I am using Echo.
Hello world.
How are you today?
I am fine.
And how are you?
I'm just typing some, some stuff here
and I'm repeating my command
to show you Alt + B for backwards.
That will be the option key
if you're on Mac keyboard,
or Alt + F for forwards,
but I don't wanna go forwards.
I want to go all the way back.
So Control + A for all
the way to the beginning.
So this is all you need to know
about all these convenient
keyboard shortcuts.
Let's continue.