- In this video, I wanna tell
you about shell expansion.
So, what is shell expansion?
Well, that's something that allows
for more efficient command line use,
and there are different option.
To start with, there's
what we call globbing.
Globbing, also refer to as wildcards,
expense file names based on wildcards
are better based on patterns,
like ls*, which is using
the star for any pattern
or ls a?*.
Question mark stands for
one single character,
any character.
Or whether you think of ls [a-e],
which is specifying your range.
So this would show all the
files that have a name starting
with A, B, C, D, or E.
There are also other types of expansion
like brace expansion.
In brace expansion, you are going to
expand everything between the braces.
The touch command for
instance, is creating files.
And if you touch file file one,
you create file one, but file 1..9.
If the one nine are between
the curly braces, well,
you will see nine files is what you get.
You can also do that for
a comma separated list.
You can use still the expansion
which is for the home directory
or command substitution
which is where you are
going to use the result
of one command in another command.
Unless there is variable substitution,
which you can use to check the
current value of a variable.
And all of these are
examples of shell expansion
where the shell is going to interpret
what you have just typed.
Let's go check this out.
All right.
To start with, let me use LS.
Now, if anything is LS and LS star,
do you see the difference?
Well, there is a difference
and that is that the star
is showing the directory,
the directory names,
item by item.
Now I don't want LS to
do any smart things.
So I'm adding the option minus D,
I'll tell you about this minus D later,
and that'll show you the same as LS star.
Now, what if I use LS?
And we should do that on
the directory that contains
a couple more files, LS
slash etc star for instance.
These are all fells in the etc directory.
Now what if I would use
LS minus D, etc, a star,
all files that have a
name starting with an a.
And if I make that a
question, mark question mark,
question mark, question mark.
Four question mark, star,
have a look etc alsa
in the second column to the
bottom, it's no longer there.
It doesn't match the
pattern, which is an a
followed by four characters, followed by
no matter how many other characters.
Also an interesting,
well, is LS slash etc,
oops, let's keep the minus D, slash etc,
between braces a E star, which
is showing files of the namea
starting with an A, B, C, D, or E.
I like the brace extension.
What do you think, for instance, of touch?
Have we already talked about touch?
I don't think so.
Okay, quick demo of touch.
Touch hello is doing what?
It's creating a file with the
name, hello, an empty file.
And that's convenient, you can use touch
to verify, right, ability.
What do you think of touch
hello, curly brace 1..100000?
Is it going to work?
In fact, I should say I don't hope so.
I'm using control C
because as you can see,
it has it has done a lot, oh boy.
Now I need to show you rm on hello.
Hello what?
Well, hello star should do
it to remove everything,
and removing almost a
hundred thousand files
as you can see is quite some
work, but they are gone.
Now, I also like command substitution.
We have, for instance, which passwd,
which is showing the full path
name of the passwd command.
And if I wanna see properties
of that, I can use LS minus L,
of course, I can type user being passwd,
but I can also put my
command between braces.
So LS minus L, which passwd
is showing the long listing
of this command.
And last but not least,
let's explore a variable.
Echo dollar path, which is
showing the current contents
of the path variable.
Variables are convenient
parts of the operating system
that store stuff that
changes all the time.
And here you can see how to
address one of these variables.
More about variables later.
About shell expansion?
Well, we have seen enough for now.