- In this video, we'll talk
about special characters
that need to be escaped.
Now, what is escaping all about?
Well, we have seen it in expansion,
special characters are
interpreted by the shell
to attribute a special
meaning to the variables.
And in escaping, this special
meaning is taken away.
There are three different
ways to use escaping.
Double quotes to start with,
they suppress globbing and shell expansion
but do allow command and
variable substitution,
so they're quite weak.
Single quotes take away
the special meaning
of any characters.
And backslash protects the
following character only
from expansion.
Let me show you.
Okay, let me show you
first, ls -l myfile output,
which is using the ls command
with two different arguments.
Now, what if I put these
arguments between double quotes?
Then we can get an error message,
no such file or directory,
because the double quotes
take away the meaning
of the spaces, and that is what they do.
Now, how about echo $PATH?
Well, here we can see $PATH is interpreted
and if I don't want
$PATH to be interpreted
I can put it between single quotes.
Single quotes work here,
double quotes don't,
because double quotes don't
take away the meaning of a $.
But as in this case,
it's only one character
that I want to take away the meaning for.
I might also use a
backslash for the escaping.
There we go, that's all you
need to know about escaping.