- In this video, we are
going to explore variables.
The mission of a variable is
to separate site specific data
from generic code
and the shell comes with
standard system variables
in the environment
to get an overview
of these system variables you can type env
for environment.
Users can define variables
themselves as well.
Using export key is value.
Defining your own
variables is mainly useful
in scripting
to make variables persistent,
they should be stored in
the Bash startup files.
I'll tell you more about those later.
Let's go check out some variables.
So let's start with the command env
env for environment.
And in the environment we say
we can see different settings,
like no terminal session
and user,
the current user,
and so many more
which all relates to the
current state of the system.
This is where the operating system is
getting its own values from.
And we have seen already
a couple of them like HIST
if I use echo dollar HIST
and then I hit the tab key,
then what do we see?
I see all the variables that
cause that start with HIST
like HIST size
1000 for the history
size or echo dollar path
which is the current path
that the operating system is using.
I can also define my own variables
by using
key equals value.
And next I can use echo dollar
followed by the name of the key
to request the current value.
But the thing is that this
variable is a local variable.
If I would start another
shell like a sub shell
as well I've done right now
and I use echo dollar color again,
I don't see it anymore.
And that's why if you
want to set variables,
well first you need to do it
through some of the Bash startup files
because that makes sure they
are available everywhere.
But even if you want to set them
on the command line,
at least use export.
So if I use exports,
color equals green for instance
and then I go to a sub shell
and I use echo dollar color again,
at least I can see this variable still,
but that works for sub shells,
not in new shells that you are opening
because if right now I'm
using echo dollar color
then I'm getting nothing.
As I said,
if you really want these
variables to be persistent
you should set them in
the Bash startup files.