- In this video, we'll
be talking about alias.
Alias is a solution that best providing
which allows you to define
your own custom commands.
That can be useful.
Some commands defined
as an alias are provided
as a system default
and to get an overview,
you can just type alias.
Also, you can define them
yourselves like alias key is value
which will define your own alias.
It's a little bit like
defining a variable just
with the word alias in front of it.
For instance, use alias
del='rm -rf /' don't forget
the single quotes here to avoid
any interpretation problems.
If at one point in time
you don't want to use your
aliases anymore, use unalias.
Custom aliases that are provided
by the operating system are stored
in the Bash startup files.
Let's go have a look at some examples.
If I type alias
then I get a list of all
the aliases that exist.
So zgrep, do I really want to use zgrep?
ps aux | zgrep ssh.
Well, as you can see, it works.
If I don't like it, unalias zgrep.
That's one alias that
I'm never using myself.
Probably more comfortable
is to define your own alias.
So alias
del=rm '-rf /tmp'.
Let's not do it on slash
because that will be a
very dangerous command
if you run it the wrong way.
Now, if I type alias
then I should be able to see
my del command right here.
And if I now am going
to run my del command,
Hmm, maybe not a very good idea.
So unalias del, and
let's do something else
like alias del='hello world'.
Hello world, that's not a command,
must be a command.
So now I can use del to show you
that at least it's working.