- While working with bash,
the bash environment is pretty important.
This is a couple of configuration files
that is stored to offer generic options
that apply to everybody,
as well as use user specific options.
So there's a couple of files
you should be aware of.
/etc/profile is a
generic bash startup file
containing all systems settings
that are processed in a login shell.
/etc/bashrc is processed
while opening a subshell.
And in case you are wondering
what's the difference,
while the login shell is what is happening
when a user authenticates,
and a subshell is any time
a command is opening its
temporary environment
to do its work.
So in fact, the subshell is
probably far more important.
Then we have ~/.bash_profile,
~ is the home directory,
so you can guess what this is about.
This is about use a specific
version of /etc/profile.
Use it for anything that
applies to specific users only.
Likewise for ~/.bashrc.
If at any time you want to make sure
that variables and alias are persistent,
it's a good idea to use
custom startup files.
Let's go check out some of these files.
So to start with /etc/profile,
it's the mother of all environment files.
As you can see right here, it
contains bash scripting code.
And this is really not
something that you should be
tuning for yourself.
Also interesting is that
in this /etc/profile
what we see right here,
if it can find a file
with the name /etc/bashrc then /etc/bashrc
is going to be sourced, it's
going to be included as well.
/etc/bashrc is for all of these settings
that you want to be available
in all of your subshells.
And as you can see, we have
even more comments and settings,
and stuff that is being created.
Now in current Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
you will deal with
configuration files a lot,
but many of these configuration files
are managed through rpm packages.
And in order to deal with
changes through the packages
you are supposed to keep your
own changes somewhere else.
Normally you will find
it directly with the name
/etc/name of the file.d
So if I go there and I use ls,
and then I can see some
of these dropping files
that further tune the behavior
of your bash environment.
If you want to make your own changes,
you should do that in the .bash files
in your home directory.
Let me type vim .bash,
and then use step completion
to show you what we have.
So that's bash_profile and bashrc.
So in my bashrc, we can see,
oh, it's globally importing something
and it's doing more stuff.
And well, if I want to
put my alias in here,
alias hello='hello world',
for instance, then here we go.
Does that also make it effective?
Well, let's have a look, alias,
and I don't see my alias hello.
And that is because this
bashrc is really included
when we start a new shell.
Like I use bash and there we go,
hello, and oh no, hello command not found.
Does that make sense?
Yes that made sense because I had a typo.
Alias hello='hello world'.
What is hello world?
That's not a command.
Shall we make that 'echo hello world'?
So that at least it can do something.
That's how you would do it.