- Okay, so in this lab,
we really need to tweak
the Bash environment.
The big question is,
do I really want to do that for everybody?
I don't think so.
So let me have a look at .bash_profile,
we didn't have a look at that one yet.
I just wanted to show you,
get the alias and functions,
and user specific environment,
and startup programs.
That looks good.
So I am going to use export.
Export color is red to start with.
Then we need to create an alias, so alias,
(computer keyboard clacking)
alias dir=,
between single quotes,
very important, 'ls - ltr'.
"ls - ltr" is a nice way
of sorting files by modification time.
And next ensure that the Bash history file
can grow to a maximum
size of 2,500 entries.
What do you think?
Is that something that we
can do for individual users?
Let's just try it.
Export HIST,
(computer keyboard clacking)
HIST FILE SIZE is 2,500.
There we go.
Now we need to make sure
that this new .bash_profile
is going to be effective.
How do we do that? Maybe by sourcing it.
I'm using source .bash_profile.
That's something that I
haven't explained yet,
so let me explain.
If you use source,
you really include the
contents of a shell script,
a shell environment file.
So if that was successful
then I should be able to use
dir, and well, that is working.
And how about echo HIST FILE SIZE?
Yeah, we have HIST file size set to 2,500.
Now last, the variable $color,
and as you can see, color is set to red.
Now with this, we haven't
only completed the lab,
we have also seen something
else that's very interesting.
We have HIST FILE SIZE.
HIST FILE SIZE is a
generic system variable.
Even the generic system variables
can be overwritten at
a user specific level,
which is what we have just done.