- Welcome to lesson two,
installing Red Hat
Enterprise Linux server.
In this lesson, you'll
learn what is needed
to install Red Hat Enterprise
Linux in your environment.
I'll first explain what is
needed to install RHEL nine.
After which, we can cover the
actual installation itself.
I'll cover all the
parameters that are needed
to set up a basic system,
which also includes an installation
with custom partitioning.
You'll also learn how to deploy a Red Hat
in a Cloud environment.
And when we reach the end of this lesson,
you'll have your own environment
that is ready for use.
At the end of this
lesson, you'll find a lab
that allows you to
practice RHEL installation,
as well as the lab solution.