- All right.
Let's talk about server requirements.
So, what you are going to need
to install Red Hat Enterprise
Linux really depends
on the type of insulation
that you are going to do.
So, is it a physical, a cloud,
or a virtual insulation?
Are you going to use a
graphical user interface or not?
And what exactly are you
going to do with the server?
And if you have the
answers to all of these,
then you can talk about your requirements.
Now for this class, we
will make it really simple.
I recommend you use a virtual machine
with the following specs.
So, here are the requirements
for installation in this class.
To start with, you need at
least two gigabytes of RAM.
You are going to need a
graphical user interface,
and that doesn't work well if
you only have one gigabyte.
Make sure you have 20
gigabytes of disk space.
Also, make sure you have
a network connection
and an optical drive
or access to a DVD ISO.
In the next video,
you will learn how to
perform a basic installation.