- [Instructor] So once you
have booted your machine
from the Red Hat Enterprise
Linux 9 installation media,
this is what you get.
By default, it wants you
test the installation media
before you can install.
I would suggest not to do that.
Just select, "Install Red
Hat Enterprise Linux 9."
Now, you will see the blinking
cursor for a few seconds
and then it starts loading
the installation system.
And here we have access to
the graphical installation.
Okay, so to start with,
we need to select a language, English.
English, United States,
is the only language
that makes sense.
For your service, it's nice
to know that you can install
in a different language, but for the exam,
that's really not something to do.
And here we can see the
Installation Summary screen.
Now, the nice thing about the
Installation Summary screen
is that you only have to provide choices
for the things that are different.
And if you really want to
go for the minimal options,
you only have to follow the links in red.
So, we need to select
Installation Destination.
By default, it wants to
do automatic partitioning
and there's an exclamation mark here.
That is because the installer
is going to override your entire disk.
You can see the disk that it has found,
a 20 gigabyte disk in VMware,
which is known as sda.
And the storage configuration
is set to automatic,
and that's perfect.
I just have to click "Done" here
to tell the software
installer that we are good
and that it's okay to
override the entire disk.
The next required option is
related to the user settings.
This is about the root password.
The root is your system administrator user
and this user needs a password.
So, let me enter a password
and I need to enter the
same password twice.
Notice that the installer has detected
that I have a weak password.
I wanna have a weak password,
I don't care about it
for this demo system.
And that is why in the
lower part it's telling me
that I need to click "Done" twice
to accept the weak password.
Also, there is an option
if I want to do, "Lock the root accounts,"
that you can only log in
using an administrative user
and an option that you need to separately
specify to allow a root
SSH login with password.
By default, the root user
cannot use Secure Shell
to connect to your server.
I am going to click
done twice because this
is exactly matching what I need.
And then I will have a quick
look at three other options.
There are many more options available,
but only a few more that matter.
To start with the networking,
we can see that my wired
network connection is connected
and that's all that I want to verify.
I obtained an IP address
from the DHCP server.
My server is connected,
so I'm clicking "Done."
You don't even have to set a host name,
we'll take care of that later.
The next option is the Software Selection,
where it is going to select server
with graphical user interface.
I think that's the option
you wanna use as well
in order to get familiar with
Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
But very commonly used
are the Server option
and the Minimal installation,
which don't offer you access
to any graphical user interface.
But here, we are just going
to keep it for while it is.
And about the choice
for additional software,
that's not something
you have to worry about.
We can do that later.
So let me click "Done."
And last but not least, the time zone.
America, Chicago time zone.
Well, depends on where you are.
It is nice to set your server
to a time that matches
your local time zone.
So let me do that and then click "Done."
And next, we can click
"Begin Installation,"
which is starting the installation.
And this is the part that
takes at least five minutes.
Alright, the installation is now done.
So let's click "Reboot System," to reboot.
One of the first things that you will see
after rebooting is the GRUB boot loader.
In this GRUB boot loader,
you can see your current kernel version
and there's also a rescue system.
We're not going to use a rescue system,
so I'm just going to press
enter on the default selection.
This GRUB boot loader is going
to be very important later on
because you can use it to
pass specific boot options,
which can be useful if
anything doesn't work out
the way you expect it to be.
So, here we can see the set of wizards.
You need to go through it and
indicate what you wanna do.
There's not much
interesting happening here
apart from the "About You."
This is where you create a
user account for yourself.
I like using a user
with the name "Student,"
and I suggest you do the same
because throughout the
exercises in this course,
I will refer to the user account as well.
This user will be provided
with pseudo privileges as well.
And it means that this
user will have options
to do administrative work.
So, that's all.
Now you click "Start Using
Red Hat Enterprise Linux,"
and that'll bring you into the
main application interface.
I would suggest you to say, "No, thanks,"
on Take Tour to get access to your system.
We'll take care of the
registration later on as well.
For now, we are all good.