- All right.
We have just seen how to
do a basic installation.
In many cases, you don't
wanna do a basic installation,
but you might want to
do custom partitioning.
Let's talk about the need
for custom partitioning
before I'm going to show you.
So Linux service typically,
multiple storage volumes are used.
You will learn that
different options exist
for these storage volumes.
Like partitions, which
are the base solution
for offering multiple
separate storage areas.
Another option is to use logical volumes,
which can be used as
alternatives to partitions.
And you will learn later
about them in lesson 19.
Now, whatever you are
doing, in most cases,
a small partition containing
all that is required
for booting is created,
and a root partition,
which contains the operating
system should be there.
And other file types
that are often organized
on dedicated partitions are log files,
and user home directories,
and server document roots,
and the location for
container images, and more.
And the reason, well, you just want them
to be strictly separated from
your core operating system.
So, custom partitioning is exactly
what we are going to do in the next demo.
Let me show you.
All right, so if you want to
install a custom partitioning,
this is where you go.
You select automatic partitioning,
and then you need to select custom.
It's a little bit counterintuitive,
but you select custom,
and then you click done.
And that'll bring you to the
RHEL installation interface.
So it's telling you,
new mount points will use
following partition scheme.
I don't want to use LVM, I want
to use standard partitions.
And then you can create all of
these partitions one by one.
So I'm clicking plus.
To start with, I want to
create a partition for /boot.
Notice that they can
conveniently be selected
from the dropdown list.
And I'm giving it the size of 500M.
500M, that is good enough.
The installer will understand.
Let's not worry about
all the other options
that we see right here like file system.
It is just using XFS, which
is a default file system.
And default file system is okay.
Next, I would like to have
a root partition, the slash.
And I give it a size of 12 gigabytes.
And then, many times on your server,
you also want a swap partition.
So let's use one G of swap.
And finally, let's add another partition,
which is using three gigabytes
for home, for instance.
So you click at mount
points, then you click, done.
And once you have clicked,
done, you will get an overview.
So the only thing remaining
is to accept changes,
and that will bring you back
to the main installation window
from which you can
continue the installation
as we have seen before.