- So at this point,
you should have a ready
to be used instance of
Red Hat enterprise Linux.
What are we going to do with it?
Well, you first need to log into it.
To work on Linux,
you need to identify yourself,
and you do that by logging
in using a user account.
Let's know that procedure.
You do that on your own computer as well.
A user account is created when
the server installs.
Some service have a root user account
with unlimited access privileges,
and some service only have
a regular user account
that can perform administrative
tasks using sudo.
And some service have both.
The server that we have installed
in the previous video does
have a root user account,
and a regular user account.
And that's exactly what I need you to have
at this specific moment.
But I can already tell you
before we dive into further details
that you should avoid logging in as root,
because it has a higher risk
of security related problems.
So let me show you how to log in,
and what you can do after that.
Okay, so we can see the
student user account.
It's user account that I've created,
and you need to enter a password
for that student user account.
And that will bring you
into the graphical user interface.
For now, please ignore the message
about the system that
has not been registered.
We are only going to do that much later.
So what we see here is
what we call the GNOME
graphical user interface.
And in this interface,
well, there's only one
thing that really matters,
and that's a terminal,
because in the terminal,
you are going to do
everything you need for RHCSA.
So at this point,
you are ready to get started
with Red Hat enterprise Linux.
In the next lesson,
you will learn what to
do once you are here.