- Okay, before we continue,
I want to talk a little bit
about using RHEL in Cloud.
The most important thing
that you should notice
is that using RHEL in Cloud is different.
To start with, in Cloud, RHEL
is deployed, not installed.
And also, a very important difference
is that the Cloud provides
the boot procedure, not Linux.
And different procedures are used
by different Cloud providers.
And because of all these
differences, in this class,
you should not be using a Cloud instance.
If you want to become an RHCSA,
you need to be able to access
your booting RHEL system
if anything goes wrong in the
boot, in the boot procedure.
So, you need access to a grip boot prompt,
and in most cases, in
Cloud, that is not the case.
So, really, using a RHEL instance in Cloud
is not a good idea to
get you ready for RHCSA.