- All right, so to start with,
you need to select, Install
Red Hat Enterprise Linux 9.0.
If you don't, doesn't really change a lot
but you will need to
wait a little bit longer
while the integrity of the
installation media is verified.
So, you need to select
the installation language,
set to English.
And then one of the most important option
is the Installation Destination.
We are not going to use
the automatic installation,
we need custom.
So you select Custom.
Then you click Done.
Next, you select Standard
Partitioning and you click +.
So, the Mount Point that
must be /boot to start with.
And I know that wasn't
even asked for in the lab,
so we don't do /boot.
We just do a 10 gigabyte root partition.
So, you click at Mount Point
and then you repeat the procedure
by creating a one gigabyte swap partition.
You will learn all about why
this might be useful later
in this course, for this
moment you just need to do it.
So, I'm already done in the partitioning
which means I can click Done.
And have a look at the
overview of the changes
and if that looks okay,
click Accept Changes.
Next, we need to make sure that
server with GUI is installed.
That automatically happens.
So, no changes needed here.
You need to make sure
that your server is
connected to a network.
As you can see my network card
which is named ens160 is connected
and it already has an IP address.
So that's good.
Also, no changes needed here
and we need to set a
password for the root user.
So, going once, going twice
and I'm clicking Done and Done again
because the password is too
simple, that's on purpose.
And then we need to wait until
the installation is done.
After the installation
you can create a user account to be used
throughout this course.
Okay, at this point
the installer is prompting
to reboot the system.
So, let's reboot the system.
Okay, so here we can see the last bit,
that's the get started,
where you click yes and Next
and Next to accept many things
but you still need to create your account.
So, let's see About You part,
where you provide your username,
the password that you want to use.
And after creating that user account
you can start using Red
Hat Enterprise Linux.
So, in the next lesson, you will learn
all about what you can do on
this Red Hat Enterprise Linux.